<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abdias the prophet, interpreted by T.B. fellovv of Magdalene College in Oxforde. Seene and allowed according to the order appoynted</title>
            <author>Brasbridge, Thomas, fl. 1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109671</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845318</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845318</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16641)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 178:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abdias the prophet, interpreted by T.B. fellovv of Magdalene College in Oxforde. Seene and allowed according to the order appoynted</title>
                  <author>Brasbridge, Thomas, fl. 1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[114] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Binneman, for George Bishop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1574.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.B. = Thomas Brasbridge.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G [chi]¹.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf, bound after G8.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Obadiah --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:1"/>
            <p>¶ Abdias the Prophet, Interpreted by T.B. fellovv of Magdalene College in Oxforde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed according to the order appoynted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jmprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> by Henry Binneman, for George Biſhop. 1574.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honorable my ſingular good Lorde, the Earle <hi>of Huntingdon, Preſident of the Queenes</hi> Maieſties Counſell eſtabliſhed in the North partes. &amp;c. Encreaſe of grace, and peace in Chriſt, and continuance in the ſame vnto the ende.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, I confeſſe that for lack of skil in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, &amp; of knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, I am vnfit to preſent any thing in vvriting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordſhip, vvherein diuine eloquence ought to be ſhevved, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your honor hath been practiſed theſe many yeres (as I may ſay) in continuall hearing and reading of the beſt learned, both of this Realme and other Realmes: vvhereby you are able to iudge, and to correct that vvhich is either vnaptly or vntruely
<pb facs="tcp:10210:3"/> ſayde of any man, concerning the knowledge of God and his true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Notvvithſtanding, conſidering my dutie tovvards your honor, and alſo your accuſtomed gentleneſſe in accepting aſwel the good wil of them which according to their habilitie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer but a mite, as alſo the great lerning of thoſe Diuines, vvhich in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons &amp; writings do much excel the moſt parte of thoſe Paſtors that are not vnprofitable inſtructors of the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>learned: I am ſo bold as to offer vnto your Lordſhip this ſhort expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Prophet Abdias, which not long ſince I haue vttred priuatly to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, I hope, of a few, &amp; nowe (if your Lordſhip will voutſafe to be the patron of ſo ſmal, &amp; ſo rude an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of this peece of Scripture) I mind to publiſhe it to the benefite of many, if perhaps it may do them any good, into vvhoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds it ſhal come.
<pb facs="tcp:10210:3"/> In it I haue vſed the iudgement of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers learned men, whoſe words I haue tranſlated out of Latin into Engliſhe, and haue diſpoſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this Treatiſe, as I haue thought good. Therfore the doctrine therin conteined, vvhich is ſound, is other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: the maner of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, vvhiche is rude, is mine. That which is lacking in the maner of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, is reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penced in the truthe of the doctrine. As the doctrine is true, ſo it maketh the words of the Prophet plain vnto the ſimple &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t people: and alſo it helpeth not a little to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the other Prophets, and of diuers places of the Scripture therein recited, and giueth ſome good inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions perteyning to fayth and good vvorks. Therefore although it be but a ſmall and ſhorte Treatiſe, it maye ſerue by the vvorking of the holy Ghoſt, bothe to the encreaſe of diuine knovvledge, and alſo of a godly life, in as manye as ſhall take paynes too
<pb facs="tcp:10210:4"/> reade it. My duetie tovvardes your Lordſhip, moued me to dedicate it to your honor: that as through the helpe of your bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifulneſſe, many ignorant people are much inſtructed in diuers places in the word of God, by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel: ſo by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſuccor towards the publiſhing of this little booke, many may ſomthing augment their knowledge in the holy ſcriptures, by reading the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this Prophet. How ſo euer it ſhall pleaſe God to vvorke, my minde is to beſtovv that little talent that God hath giuen me, to the ſetting foorth of hys glory, and to the profit of his Church, not neglecting your Lordſhips ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: Muche encreaſe vvhereof God graunt you in this vvorlde, and in the vvorlde to come euerlaſting bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, through Chriſte our Lorde.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſeruant and dayly orator. <hi>T. B.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>The .xxi of Auguſt. 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:4"/>
            <head>The propheſie of Abdias, tranſlated out of the Hebrue into Engliſhe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE viſion of Obadiah. This hath the Lorde Iehoua ſayde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Edom, we haue heard a voyce from Iehoua, that an Embaſſadour is ſent among the Nations (ſaying) vp, and let vs ariſe agaynſt hir vnto battell.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Beholde, I haue made thee of ſmall power, and of little reputation among the Nations, thou art greatly deſpiſed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The pride of thy heart hath deceyued thee which dwelleſt in the caues of a rocke, hauing an highe place for his habitation, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his heart: who ſhall bring me downe to the grounde?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Although thou mount like an Eagle, yea although thou make thy neſt among the ſtarres, from thence will I bring thee downe: this is a ſure ſaying of Iehoua.</p>
            <p n="5">5 If theeues ſhoulde come vnto thee, or robbers by night, howe miſerably ſhouldeſt thou be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled? (yet) would they not ſteale (onely) ſo muche as ſhould be ſufficient for
<pb facs="tcp:10210:5"/> them? if grape gatherers ſhould come vnto thee, would they not leaue ſome ſmall ones?</p>
            <p n="6">6 O how are the goodes of Eſau ſoughte vp and his treaſures ſpoyled?</p>
            <p n="7">7 All the men that were confederate with thee, haue driuen thee to the borders, the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were at peace with thee, haue deceyued thee, they haue preuayled agaynſt thee: they that haue had mayntenance by thee, ſhall laye a ſnare in thy waye to catche thee: he ſhall not perceyue it.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Shall not I at that day (ſayth the Lord) cut off from Edom the wiſe men, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding from the mount of Eſau?</p>
            <p n="9">9 Ye moreouer the corage of thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie captaynes (O Teman) ſhall bee abated, bicauſe euery man ſhall be cut off from the mount of Eſau by ſlaughter.</p>
            <p n="10">10 For the cruell ſpoyling of thy brother Iacob, thou ſhalt be put to ſhame, yea thou ſhalt periſhe for euer.</p>
            <p n="11">11 At what tyme thou ſtoodeſt a loofe off, at what tyme ſtrangers caried away his ſubſtance, and aliants entred into his gates, and caſt lots vpon Ieruſalem, then thou waſt euen as one of them.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <pb facs="tcp:10210:5"/>12 But thou ſhouldeſt not haue beholden the day of thy brother, the day in the which he was caried into exile, neyther ſhouldeſt thou haue laughed at the inhabitants of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huda, in the day of their deſtruction, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhouldeſt thou haue triumphed ouer them in the day of their affliction.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Thou ſhouldeſt not haue entred into the gates of my people, in the day of their deſtruction, neyther ſhouldeſt thou then haue beholden his miſerie in the day of his deſtruction, neyther ſhouldeſt thou haue layde handes vpon his ſubſtance in the day of his deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Neither ſhouldeſt thou haue ſtande in the croſſe wayes to ſlay thoſe that otherwiſe had eſcaped, neyther ſhouldeſt thou then haue taken priſoners thoſe that remayned of them in the day of affliction.</p>
            <p n="15">15 For the day of Iehoua is at hand vpon all Nations, euen as thou haſt done, it ſhall be done vnto thee: thy miſcheeuous dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhall returne vpon thy owne pate.</p>
            <p n="16">16 For euen as you haue drunke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine holy hil, ſo al nations ſhal drinke continually, yea they ſhall drinke, and ſwalow vp, &amp; they
<pb facs="tcp:10210:6"/> ſhal be as though they had not beene at all.</p>
            <p n="17">17 But vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mount Sion there ſhal be ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and it ſhal be holy: and the houſe of Iacob ſhall receyue their poſſeſsions.</p>
            <p n="18">18 And the houſe of Iacob ſhal be a fyre, &amp; the houſe of Ioſeph a flame, &amp; the houſe of Eſau as ſtubble, and they ſhall kindle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and conſume them, and there ſhall be none left of the houſe of Eſau, for Iehoua hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p n="19">19 And they ſhal poſſeſſe the ſouth ſide of the mount of Eſau, and the champion coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of the Philiſtines, and they ſhall poſſeſſe the feelden countrey of Ephraim, and the feelden countrey of Samaria, and Beniamin (ſhall poſſeſſe) Gilead.</p>
            <p n="20">20 And they of this hoſt of the Iſraelites, that are in captiuitie among the Canaanites, ſhal poſſeſſe vnto Sarephath, and they of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are in captiuitie in Sephared, ſhall poſſeſſe the cities of the South.</p>
            <p n="21">21 And there ſhal come vp in mount Sion ſauiours, to giue ſentence agaynſt the mount of Eſau, &amp; Iehoua ſhal haue the kingdome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="paraphrase">
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:6"/>
            <head>A briefe Paraphraſis of Abdias propheſie.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Propheſie following concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the deſtruction of the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, &amp; deliuerance of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites out of captiuitie, was reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Abdias, and declared to him in a viſion, for the conſolation and comforte of Gods children, and this is the effect thereof. Thus ſayth the Lorde Iehoua, the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, agaynſt the Edomites, the cruell enimies of his people Iſraell. This not I only, but Ieremy and the other Prophets haue heard the Lorde Iehoua ſay (who is mightie &amp; hath care of his people, whoſe words are moſt certain and true, and whom no man is able to reſiſt) he hath ſayd that an Embaſſadour (euen the ſonne of God, by whome the world is ruled, &amp; whome all men muſt obey) is ſent among the Nations: whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion is to rayſe them vp vnto war, and to prouoke them vnto battell agaynſt the Edomites: and he him ſelfe will be cheefe in the warre agaynſt them, whome it ſhall be an eaſie matter to ouercome. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For God hath diminiſhed their power, and hath made them one of the leaſt people among other nations. Yea he hath brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght them into contempt, and hath made them of no reputation among men of other countreys. Therfore they are not of ſuche power &amp; ſtrength as they take them ſelues to bee. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Their proude heart hath deceyued them, and hath taken away their vnderſtanding, ſo that they do not knowe them ſelues, nor ſee their owne weakneſſe. They thinke them ſelues ſtrong inoughe agaynſt all
<pb facs="tcp:10210:7"/> men, bicauſe they dwell in the rockes and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes. Therefore they perſuade them ſelues that no Nation is able too preuayle agaynſt them, and to bring them too deſtruction. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But althoughe their habitation were muche hygher than it is, although they could make their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as highe as the Eagle can flye, yea as high as the Starres, yet almightie God (whoſe habitation is higher, and whoſe power is aboue theirs) ſayth for a certentie, that he will bring them downe from thence, yea that he wyll take away all their ſubſtance, and vtterly deſtroy them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> If theeues and robbers ſhould come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a man by nighte, he ſhoulde bee miſerably handled, yet they woulde take away no more, than that is ſufficient for them. If robbers of Vineyardes ſhoulde come, and ſpoyle a mans grapes, they woulde not take all, they woulde leaue ſome little ones at the leaſt behinde them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> But it can not be expreſſed how the goodes and ſubſtance of Eſaus poſteritie ſhall be ſoughte out, and howe all his Iuels and Treaſures ſhall be ſpoyled and cleane taken away. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall there be any man to helpe them. For all their confederates ſhall forſake them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their enimies. They that had made peace with them, haue deceyued them with their flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering wordes: yea and they in whome they truſted moſte, as vnto whome they haue beene beneficiall, they that haue liued vpon their coſt, and whom they haue enterteyned in wages for their defence, they (I ſay) haue layde a ſnare in their waye to catche them, and ſhall bring them to deſtruction: yea and that ſodenly, ſo that they ſhall not perceyue it, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their great wiſedome and pollicie. For
<pb facs="tcp:10210:7"/> God whiche is the geuer of all good giftes, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> taketh them away at hys pleaſure, ſhall take away their wyſe men, and theyr wyſedome from them. So that there ſhall not be a man of vnderſtanding lefte among them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hee wyll abate the courage of their ſtrong men, of their Gyaunts and mightie Captay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, bicauſe he hathe determined vtterly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the inhabitantes of Idumea with the ſworde: bothe wyſe, and fooliſhe, ſtrong and weake, riche and poore, yong and olde, man, woman, and childe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Bicauſe of their cruell dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in ſpoyling their kinſmen and brethren, the poſteritie of Iacob. They ſhall bee brought to ſhame and diſhonour, yea they ſhall periſhe for euer. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> When ſtraungers and aliants entered into the cities of the Iſraelites, and caried away their ſubſtance, the Edomites ſtoode aloofe of pretending friendſhip, but in deede they tooke parte wyth their enimies. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> But they ſhoulde not gladly haue beholden that miſerable daye of their brethren, in the whiche they were made captiues in a ſtraunge Countrey, they ſhoulde not haue laughed at them, nor haue tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed ouer them in this their affliction. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhoulde they haue entred into the gates of Gods people with their enimies, to be partakers with them of the ſpoyle. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Much leſſe ſhould they haue ſtande in the croſſe wayes to kill and ſlay thoſe that otherwyſe mighte haue eſcaped the ſword, neyther ſhould they haue ſtopped and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners thoſe that remayned vntaken of their enimies, at ſuche time as it pleaſed God to afflicte them. But thus cruelly they dydde
<pb facs="tcp:10210:8"/> handle the people of God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> Of whiche wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he will be reuenged very ſhortly. For the day which Iehoua, the Lord our God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for that purpoſe, is at hande. In the whiche he will take vengeance of all Nations that are enimies vnto his children. And euen as they handled the Iſraelites, ſo ſhal they be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. The ſame meaſure that they haue mette to other, ſhall be mette to them: the miſcheefe that they haue ordeyned for other men, ſhall fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them ſelues. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> For euen as Gods people haue beene afflicted in Ieruſalem, ſo ſhall all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that moleſted them be afflicted, yea they ſhall continually haue abundance of afflictions, they ſhall be ouerwhelmed, yea they ſhall be ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp, and deuoured with afflictions. The Edomites (I ſay) ſhal be vtterly deſtroyed, they ſhall be euen as thoughe they had neuer beene. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> But the Iſraelites ſhall be ſaued, the people of God ſhall be holy, and ſanctified, to worſhippe God according to his will. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> No man ſhall touch them, they ſhall be reſtored to their ſubſtance, and ſhall quietly enioy their poſſeſſions. And euen as the fyre conſumeth the ſtubble, ſo ſhall the Iſraelites haue dominion ouer their deadly enimies, the Edomites, and ſhall deſtroy them, ſo that none of them ſhall be lefte aliue. For Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houa the Lord our God hath ſpoken it, in whom there is no falſhoode, nor vnhabilitie too bring that to paſſe whiche he hathe determined. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> And Gods people, hauing vanquiſhed Eſaus poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſhall take poſſeſſion of their Countrey, euen from the one ſide to the other. They ſhall poſſeſſe both the mountaynes of the Edomites, and alſo
<pb facs="tcp:10210:8"/> the champion countrey of the Philiſtines, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their owne countrey of Iewry and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria. They ſhall poſſeſſe from the South to the Northe, and from the Weſt to the Eaſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Euen thoſe Iſraelites that are nowe in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie among the Canaanites in the Southe, ſhall poſſeſſe vnto Sarepta in the North. And the inhabitantes of Ieruſalem, that are in cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie in Boſphorus in the North, ſhall inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite the cities of the South. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> For God ſhall ſet mightie Captaynes ouer hys people Iſraell, whiche ſhall ſubdue the Edomites, and ſhall be zelous followers of God, and ſhall ſet vp his true worſhippe agayne: They ſhall both inſtruct the people, and alſo compell them to follow Gods lawes.</p>
            <p>Therefore God ſhall rule, and hee ſhall be king ouer them. For they ſhal ſerue him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:9"/>
            <head>A larger interpretation of Abdias Propheſie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Propheſie was written agaynſt the Edomites, the poſteritie of Eſau: a people bordering vpon the Southe ſide of Iewry, towards Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia. They were the nexte neighbeurs of the Iſraelites, the poſteritie of Iacob. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob and Eſau, otherwiſe called Iſraell and Edom, were brethren, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſaac and Rebecca.<note place="margin">Gen. 25.22</note> When their mother was with childe with them, they did ſtriue in hir wombe, wherewith ſhe béeing moued, enquired of God what that ſtraunge fight ſhoulde meane.<note place="margin">An. mundi. 2100.</note> Anſwere was made hir, that ſhe had two Nations in hir wombe, that is to ſay: that two Nations ſhould riſe of their poſteritie, that they ſhould contende the one with the other, and the elder ſhould ſerue the yonger: that is, the Nation that ſhoulde come of the yonger brother, ſhoulde ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the poſteritie of the elder brother, and bring them in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which was
<pb facs="tcp:10210:9"/> fulfilled in king Dauids tyme:<note place="margin">2. Sa 8 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. An. mundi 2900.</note> who with his people, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſteritie of Iacob, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yonger brother, ſubdued the Edomites vnto him, and vnto his Nation: vnto whome they remayned ſubiect for the ſpace of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore yeres, vnto the reigne of Ioram,<note place="margin">2. Re 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 An mundi 3060.</note> the ſeuenth king of Iewry from Dauid. In whoſe dayes they rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and euer after hated the inhabitants of Iuda, as before their father Eſau had hated Iacob. As at other times, ſo chiefly they vttered their malitious mind, when Nabuchodonoſor beſieged Ieruſalem:<note place="margin">An. mundi. 33<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for they ioyned with him agaynſt Iuda. It is not vnlikely but that he deſired their help, bicauſe they were neare borderers, &amp; were acquaynted in the countrey. But he was not ſo deſirous of their ayde, as they were to offer it. For they reioyced greatly at the miſerie of the Iſraelites, they triumphed ouer them, and were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with the enimies in ſpoyling the citie of Ieruſalem. Yea they perſuaded them vtterly to deſtroy it. As it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: Remember the children of Edom,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> O Lorde, in the day of Ieruſalem, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:10210:10"/> ſayde, raſe it, raſe it, euen to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation thereof. By occaſion of this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and calamitie of the Iſraelites, the inhabitants of Idumea were mery and ioyfull, but Gods people were full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe and heauineſſe. Therefore almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God pitying their caſe, ſtirred vp Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias &amp; other Prophets to comfort them, by declaring vnto them the deſtruction of the Edomites, their enimies, and by foretelling their owne deliuerance out of captiuitie: which how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable a thing it was vnto them, wée may vnderſtande by our own example: who in the days of Mary our Quéene,<note place="margin">An. domini. 1553.</note> were oppreſſed with the members of Antichriſt, the deadly enimies of Gods people. At what tyme they endeuoured as much as lay in them to deſtroy the heauenly Ieruſalem, that is to ſay, the true Chriſtians, of whome they impriſoned and burned a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and the reſidue they cauſed eyther to flée into voluntarie baniſhmente, or elſe to reuolte from the Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion vnto Idolatrie, vntill it pleaſed almightie God to looke vpon them with
<pb facs="tcp:10210:10"/> his mercyfull eyes, and to call them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to repentance. If in this tyme of miſerie God had ſente vs ſome Abdias, to tell vs that he woulde deſtroy our enimies, and reſtore thoſe that were baniſhed into their ceuntrey, and aduaunce them to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and wealth, this muſt néedes haue béene very comfortable vnto vs. And ſo it came to paſſe in déede: For God dothe not in any age leaue thoſe comfortleſſe that cleaue wholly vnto him. Therfore he ſente his Prophet Abdias among the Iſraelites to ſhewe them the deſtruction of their enimies, and their owne deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of captiuitie, to comfort them, and to confirme them in the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God. This is the purpoſe of the Prophet, whoſe propheſie may be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two chapters. In the firſt God threatneth deſtruction vnto the Edomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: and in the ſeconde he promiſeth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, with great proſperitie and felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto the Iſraelites. The firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſiſteth of foure partes. In the firſt is declared the certayntie of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: In the ſeconde the ſtaye and
<pb facs="tcp:10210:11"/> arguments wherby the Edomites might perſuade them ſelues of ſafetie, are taken away and confuted. In the thirde, the greatneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> calamitie that God would ſende vpon them, is declared. And laſt of all, are ſhewed the cauſes of their deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is not impertinent to the firſt parte, to note héere the author of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie. It is called the propheſie of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias. But it was reuealed by the holy Ghoſt, euen by God him ſelfe, and vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the miniſterie of Abdias.<note place="margin">Luk. 1.69.</note> As the Prophete Zacharie ſayth: The Lorde God of Iſraell hathe rayſed vnto vs a mightie ſaluation in the houſe of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uante Dauid, as he promiſed by the mouth of his holy Prophets which were ſince the world began. And the Apoſtle that writeth to the Hebrues,<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.1.</note> ſayth: At ſundrie tymes, and in dyuers maners God ſpake in olde tyme to our fathers by the Prophets. And our Sauiour ſayth: that Dauid ſayde in the ſpirite, or by the holy Ghoſt:<note place="margin">Mat. 22.43</note> the Lorde ſayde vnto my Lorde, ſit thou on my right hande, vntill I make thy enimies thy foote ſtoole. Héere
<pb facs="tcp:10210:11"/> our Sauiour ſignifieth that Dauid ſpake not of him ſelfe, but the holy Ghoſt by his mouth. So it appeareth by the words of S. Peter,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18.</note> that Noe in his time preached vnto the people, not of him ſelfe, but our Sauiour Chriſt in his Godhead preached by the mouth of Noe. For S. Peter ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the death and reſurrection of our Sauiour, ſayth that he was mortified in the fleſhe, but quickned or rayſed to life by the ſpirite, that is to ſay by his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. In the whiche ſpirite (ſaythe he) Chriſt came and preached to the ſpirites that are in priſon, whiche were diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in the dayes of Noe. Theſe words of our Sauiour, of the Apoſtles, and of Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie, teache vs that it was our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt in Noe, the ſpirite of God in Dauid, and in the other Prophetes that ſpake vnto the people. Therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the ſame ſpirite ſpake in Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias, and that God him ſelfe was the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of his propheſie. This alſo is many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by the words of the Prophet: For he ſayth: I haue made thée of ſmal power, and of little reputation among the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb facs="tcp:10210:12"/> The Prophet had no ſuch power, as to diminiſhe the reputation and power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Edomites. Therfore it foloweth neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſpake not in his own perſon, but that almightie God ſpake himſelf by the mouth of the prophet. Therfore I ſay (which perteyneth to the firſt part of this chapter) that the deſtruction of the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites is certayne. For God himſelf is the author therof. Vnto this parte alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth the title of the propheſie, in that it is called a viſion. Of viſions there is often mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made in the Scriptures, as in the propheſies of Ieremie, Ezechiel, &amp; Daniell, and in the Reuelations of Iohn. Daniell<note place="margin">Dan. 7.1.</note> in a dreame ſawe a viſion of foure Beaſtes. And Sainct Iohn in a traunce ſaw a viſion of ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> candleſticks.<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.12</note> Of this and ſuche other viſions his whole booke of Reuelations conſiſteth. Which are declarations of things to come by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes &amp; darke kinds of ſpéech. But in this propheſie a viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is otherwiſe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded, for it ſignifieth héere a declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things to come, in playne words, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſimilitude or allegorie. As a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:10210:12"/> in olde time was called a Seer:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 9.9</note> ſo heere the propheſie of Abdias is called the ſight or viſion of Abdias.<note place="margin">2. Sa. 24.11</note> A Prophet in olde tyme was called a Seer, bicauſe he did foreſée things that ſhuld come to paſſe afterwards: ſo héere Abdias propheſie is called a viſion, bicauſe it is a thing fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene, that ſhoulde be fulfilled in tyme to come. Theſe two are both one in effecte, a Viſion, and a Propheſie, yet ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is betwéene them. For a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is a reuelation of that thing whiche God hath appoynted to bring to paſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards: and a Propheſie is an vttring of that is reuealed. As Prophets are dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, ſo are propheſies, ſome falſe, &amp; ſome true, but a viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is always certain: ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led bicauſe it is ſéene, &amp; reueled by god vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That is truly called a viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we can teſtifie that haue ſéene it. What<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer writing may truely be ſo called, it is an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined is true. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet giueth this title vnto his propheſie to declare the certentie therof. Our Sauior vſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his doctrine, ſaying:
<pb facs="tcp:10210:13"/> That which I haue ſéene I teſtifie vnto you. And after this ſort ſ. Iohn<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.38.</note> beginneth his firſt Epiſtle,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.1.</note> ſaying: That which we haue heard, which we haue ſéene with our eyes, which we haue looked vpon, whiche our hands haue handled, that declare we vnto you. The title of this propheſie is almoſt one with this title of S. Iohns E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle. For the viſion of Abdias is as much to ſay: as that whiche Abdias hath ſeene, or that whiche God hath reuealed vnto him, for a certayntie to be fulfilled in time to come. Therefore I ſay, this propheſie is called a viſion, bicauſe this worde conteyneth in it an argument, that it ſhal come to paſſe in déede, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet hath ſpoken, or rather as God hath ſpoken by the mouth of the Prophet. And bicauſe God reuealed it vnto him, it is called his viſion. At what time this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie was reuealed, or at what time Abdias vttred it, is not expreſſedly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red eyther in this booke nor in any other booke of the Scripture. The Iewes write that this was the ſame Abdias that liued in the dayes of king Ahab, and dyd ſaue
<pb facs="tcp:10210:13"/> an hundred of the true Prophets,<note place="margin">1. Re. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3. An. mundi. 3030.</note> hyding them by fiftie &amp; fiftie in a caue, and gaue them neceſſarie ſuſtenance. But the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Iewes ſéemeth contrarie to the truthe. For there is good reaſon to ſhew that Abdias liued at the ſame time that Ieremie and Ezechiell propheſied.<note place="margin">An. mundi. 3360. Ezec. 25.12 Ier. 49.7.</note> For they propheſie all agaynſt one, and the ſame people, they all declare the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and calamitie of the Edomites, and the cauſes of their deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Abdias doth agrée in words with Ieremie, as though he had learned the maner of handling his propheſie of him, as the ſcholer of the maſter. Therefore it ſéemeth that they liued and propheſied bothe at one tyme: whiche was when Nabuchodonoſor had deſtroyed Ieruſalem, and caried the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitantes thereof priſoners vnto Babilon: whiche captiuitie was full thrée hundred yeres after the reigne of Achab. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Abdias which was in his tyme could not be aliue in theſe dayes. Moſes in his prayer a lyttle before his death,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> An. mundi. 2490.</note> ſayth, that in his dayes the age of man was but thréeſcore yéeres and ten. In A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabs
<pb facs="tcp:10210:14"/> tyme it is likely that mans age was rather ſhortned than prolonged, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in his dayes the worlde was aboue fiue hundred yeres older than it was in Moſes time. For the older the world is, the ſhorter is the life of man. Althoughe ſome men liue now a dayes longer than the common ſort doe, yet the age of man commonly is but thréeſcore or foureſcore yeres. So Moſes liued an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeres. And if God in like maner were ſo beneficial to Abdias that was in Ahabs time, that he liued <hi>.40.</hi> yeres longer than the common age of man, yet he could not liue vnto the captiuitie of Babilon. For then he muſt haue liued aboue thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeres. Therfore our Abdias, and he were diuers perſons, as their ſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was diuers: for the one was a lay man, &amp; the other a Cleargie man: the one was a Courtier, &amp; the other a Prophet. But in this they do both agrée, that they might both be truly named Abdias: that is to ſay, the ſeruaunts of God. For they both did God good ſeruice: the one in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his Prophets from the cruel tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb facs="tcp:10210:14"/> of Ieſabell, and in giuing them bodily ſuſtenance, the other in vttering the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie that God had reuealed vnto him, and in feeding his people with ſpirituall foode. The foode wherewith the Prophet féedeth Gods people, is the foode of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and comforte, whiche is miniſtred by the declaration of the certayn deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their enimies, whiche is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them in theſe words: <hi>Thus hath the Lorde Iehoua ſayde.</hi> The Lorde hathe ſpoken it. <hi>Adonai</hi> is the Hebrue worde, which ſignifieth ſuch a Lorde as is an hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, a ſucourer, a preſeruer, one that is of power &amp; might, and alſo hath a care of his people. Therfore was Ioſeph called <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> bicauſe he was an helper and ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the Egyptians, bicauſe he was of great power &amp; might amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, bicauſe he had not onely a care of the people, but alſo by the pollicie &amp; wiſdome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God had giuen him they were preſerued in time of derth. Such a Lorde (ſayth the Prophet) hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe words which he vttreth vnto the people. And bicauſe there are many that are called <hi>Adonai,</hi> or Lorde,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:15"/> for difference ſake, he addeth this name <hi>Iehoua.</hi> That Lorde (ſaythe he) whoſe name is Iehoua, hathe ſpoken it, who is God, aboue all Lordes, who is almightie and ruler of all the worlde, and therefore is able to performe whatſoeuer he ſayth, and he hath alreadie ſayd it, it is alreadie determined, and therefore can not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. Although the minde of man may be changed, God is vnchangeable, he hath ſayde it, and therefore certeinly it ſhall come to paſſe. For confirmation whereof it followeth: <hi>VVe haue hearde this voyce from Iehoua.</hi> The Prophet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie<note place="margin">Ier. 49.14.</note> hath the ſame words in effect. He ſayth: I haue heard this voyce from Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houa. He ſpeaketh of him ſelfe in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular number. Although in effecte there be no more certeintie in the words of the one than of the other, yet in our eares Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias ſéemeth to ſpeake more certeinely, bicauſe he ſpeaketh in the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not of him ſelfe onely, but alſo of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophets: he ſeemeth to ſaye thus muche: Not onely God hath ſpoken it, but alſo that you may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:10210:15"/> of knowledge, I teſtifie vnto you that we haue hearde it, not onely I but alſo my fellow Prophets Ieremie and Ezechiel, for they haue propheſied the ſame things that I ſhall declare vnto you. Thus hée bringeth witneſſes of that he ſaith. That which is teſtified by two or thrée, ſéemeth vnto vnto vs more certayne than that which is witneſſed by one onely. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the better credite of his words, he ſayth: not I, but we haue herd it, and that not of any mortall man, but of Iehoua: the voyce came from almightie God, whereof I, and Ezechiel, and Ieremie are witneſſes. And this is the voyce: <hi>That an Embaſſadour is ſent among the Nations. <hi>Thir</hi>
               </hi> is the Hebrue word, which properly ſignifieth the hinges of a doore, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the doore goeth too and fro, and is thereby ruled. But figuratiuely it ſignifieth an Embaſſadour, ſuche a one as is a chiefe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the Prince, by whoſe wiſdome the common weale is ruled, and vpon whom the good eſtate of the Prince and people dothe depende. So this Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour heere mentioned is a chéefe man, by
<pb facs="tcp:10210:16"/> whom I vnderſtande the ſonne of God, the ſeconde perſon in trinitie, who is the euerlaſting wiſedome of the father,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.49</note> by whom the world was made,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.3.</note> and without who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing was made, that was made, by whom the world is gouerned, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Princes do reigne, and kings do beare rule, who ſendeth peace and warre: he is the Lorde that doth all theſe things. It is he that moueth the Nations agaynſt the Edomites to deſtroy them. All Nations muſt obey this Embaſſadour, he is not ſent to one nation, but to a multitude of Nations, they all ſhall come agaynſt the Edomites. Therfore their deſtruction is certayne. The Embaſſadour is alreadie ſent (ſayth the Prophet:) This matter is not now in conſultatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is alreadie paſt, it can not be ſtayde. His commiſſion is deliuered vnto him, and he is gone on his iourney. And this is his commiſſion, to the Nations to warre agaynſt the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, ſaying: <hi>Vp, and let vs ariſe agaynſt hir vnto battel.</hi> In Ieremie it is thus: Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your ſelues togither, come agaynſt hir, &amp; riſe to battell. In Ieremie the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour
<pb facs="tcp:10210:16"/> ſpeaketh vnto the nations, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to riſe againſt the Inhabitants of Idumea: but in our prophet Abdias, he ſpeaketh muche more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortably, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he him ſelfe will go with them vnto the warre, that he wil be a chéef cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne among them. He maketh him ſelfe one of the number, ſhewing therby that they ſhall haue his helpe, that he wil fight with them, who can compaſſe and bring to paſſe al things as pleaſeth him. Let vs (ſayth he) riſe agaynſt hir: that is to ſay, agaynſt the nation of the Edomites. God him ſelfe promiſeth to fight with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, therfore the enimies ſhal ſurely be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, &amp; his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ouercome. For if God be on our ſide, who ſhal be agaynſt vs. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former chapt. declaring the certentie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Edomites de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In the which there is to be noted a leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for al miniſters &amp; preachers of gods word, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophet entitleth his booke a viſion, &amp; in that he ſaith: Thus hath the lord Iehoua ſaid, this voyce haue we herd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iehoua: wherby is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he vttereth ſuch things only as he
<pb facs="tcp:10210:17"/> hath ſéene, and ſuche as God hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him. Suche things as he hathe heard of God, and nothing elſe but that which God hath ſpoken. This was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the maner of the Prophetes, and alſo of the Apoſtles, as appeareth in their Epiſtles, and in the reuelations of S. Iohn, not to ſpeake their owne fanſies, not to preache doctrine deuiſed by them ſelues, not to be wiſe in their owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but to teach the truthe, procéeding from God him ſelfe, and nothing elſe but that whiche he hath taught. This maner all Gods miniſters oughte to obſerue: which they ſhal do, if they ſpeake nothing raſhly and vnaduiſedly, but do diligently examine and ſearche the knowledge of God in his worde, whiche teacheth the true wiſedome,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.</note> and giueth good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, euen to the ſimple, rude, and ignorante perſons,<note place="margin">2. Ti. 3.15.</note> and (as the Apoſtle ſaythe) is able to make a man wiſe as muche as is requiſite vnto ſaluation. If Gods miniſters ſuffer their lippes to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nothing but that whiche is truely grounded vpon this worde, they may be
<pb facs="tcp:10210:17"/> bolde to ſay: Thus hath the Lorde ſayd, This voyce haue we heard fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord. This euery preacher ought not to ſay on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo it is requiſite that he be ſure that he may truly ſay it. For there are many falſe Prophets and falſe teachers, that ſay, Thus ſayth the Lord, this is the worde of God, when they teache their owne fanſies. Suche take the name of God in vayne, abuſing it for the aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of them ſelues, and the encreaſe of their owne wealth. Suche ſhall be grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly puniſhed: for God will not holde him giltleſſe that taketh his name in vayne. Therefore it is requiſite that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one whiche taketh vpon him to be a miniſter and preacher of the Goſpell, do diligently examine his doctrine by the worde of God, and then he may truly ſay with the Prophet: This hath the Lorde ſayde, and that which we haue heard we teſtifie vnto you. Then he may ſay with the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.</note> that which I receiued of the Lorde, I haue deliuered vnto you, and this is the Lords ſaying, and not myne. This is a leſſon for all the miniſters of
<pb facs="tcp:10210:18"/> Gods word, noted in this firſt part of the chapter. Héere is alſo a leſſon for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of al true Chriſtians, in that the Prophet ſignifieth that the ſonne of God the ſeconde perſon in Trinitie, is ſent as an Embaſſadour to ſtirre vp the nations to warre agaynſt Gods enimies: and in that he giueth vs to vnderſtande, that God him ſelfe will fight with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt the aduerſaries of his children: héereby we learne that God careth for his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he helpeth thoſe that call vpon him in aduerſitie, as he hath promiſed, ſaying: Call vpon me in the day of trouble,<note place="margin">Pſa. 50.15.</note> and I will deliuer thée. He fighteth for vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt our enimies, therefore they can not preuayle agaynſt vs. For it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> if God be on our ſide, who can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs? Where God taketh parte, there is the victorie. In vayne dothe any Prince make battell agaynſt his will, for all the creatures in the world are ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; beaſt, ſunne &amp; moone, fire and water, the earth, the ſea, &amp; the cloudes are at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, he vſeth al theſe things to the benefite &amp; commoditie of his
<pb facs="tcp:10210:18"/> children, and is readie alwayes to deliuer them in time of miſerie and calamitie. Concerning this matter, it is long to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the examples of Gods goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Ioſeph, Moſes, Ioſua, Dauid, Ezechias, Eſdras, the Apoſtle Paule, and many other. As in all ages, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in our remembrance, ſince the man of ſinne began to be reuealed, and the Goſpell publiſhed, the prouidence of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God in ſauing hys people, hathe béene manifeſtly ſhewed, as is to bée ſéene in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories of Germanie, of Fraunce, of Englande, and Scotlande, and diuers other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If there were nothing lefte in wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting héereof in all the worlde, yet euery man by the conſideration of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes bothe in him ſelfe, and in other menne, maye vnderſtande ſufficiently howe God careth for his people, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueryng them from their enimies, whiche is the ſeconde note for oure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, gathered oute of theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer woordes of the Prophete. In
<pb facs="tcp:10210:19"/> the firſt part of the chapter. Nowe follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the ſeconde part. <hi>Behold I haue made thee of ſmall power, and of little reputation among the Nations, thou art greatly deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> Héere God ſpeaketh vnto the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Eſau after this ſorte. Thou coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Edom, thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe ſo ſure that thou canſt not be ouerthrowne, thou perſuadeſt thy ſelfe that thou art lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of thy neighbours, and feared of thy enimies, and therefore that there is no likelyhoode that thou ſhouldeſt be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of any nation. But this loue, and this feare is but a rotten ſtaffe, or weake réede, which eaſily will be broken. For I the maker of heauen and earth, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of all the worlde, haue made thée of ſmall power, and of little reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the nations that are rounde about thée: they do vtterly contemne thée, and deſpiſe thée. I haue made thée of ſmall power (ſayth God by his Prophete) he ſpeaketh in the time paſt, of the time to come, ſignifying thereby that it ſhall as certenly come to paſſe, as though it were alredie fulfilled. Worldly Princes thinke
<pb facs="tcp:10210:19"/> their ſtate ſure, when they are loued of their neighbours, and feared of their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. But the Edomites (ſayth God) haue no ſuch aſſurance of their ſtate. For where loue is, there is reputation, but they ſhall be of ſmall reputation, therfore they ſhall not be loued, and where feare is, there is no contempt: but they ſhall be deſpiſed, therfore they ſhal not be feared. Notwithſtanding they perſuaded them ſelues of ſafetie, and did triumphe ouer other nations in their hearts, deceyuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues with a falſe perſuaſion. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet addeth, <hi>The pride of thy heart hath deceyued thee which dwelleſt in the caues of a rocke, hauing an high place for his habitation, ſaying in his heart: VVho ſhall bring me downe to the grounde?</hi> Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie<note place="margin">Ier. 49.16.</note> addeth vnto this, and ſayth moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: Thy feare, and the pride of thy heart. &amp;c. That is to ſay: the feare wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with other nations do feare thée, or elſe the opinion that thou haſt conceyued, that other nations are afrayde of thée, and the pride of thy heart hath deceyued thée. The Edomites were lifted vp with pride, they
<pb facs="tcp:10210:20"/> did aduaunce themſelues aboue other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thinking them ſelues inuincible, wheras they were of ſmall power, and of little reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore they were decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. The cauſe why they were ſo proude (as it ſéemeth by the text) was the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious ſituation of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. They did dwel on the mountaines &amp; rockes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were vnacceſſible, they had the higher grounde of their enimies, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as they thought) was able to make a forte agaynſt them, therfore they had the aduauntage of all that ſhould come againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This made them thinke with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, that no natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was able to ouercome them: therfore the Prophet ſayth: He ſayth in his heart, who ſhal bring me down to the grounde? Vnto this proud hert God anſwereth by his Prophet as foloweth: <hi>Although thou mount vp like an Eagle, yea althoughe thou make thy neſt as high as the ſtarres, euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence will I bring thee downe.</hi> This is a ſure ſaying of Iehoua. Ieremie ſayth: If thou make thy neſt as high as the Eagle, from thence will I bring thée downe. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this our Prophete addeth more, and
<pb facs="tcp:10210:20"/> ſayth: if thou make thy neſt as highe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſtarres, and ſo foorth: that is to ſay, Truſt not to thy dwelling on high, for if it were a thouſand times higher than it is thou art not able to reſiſt God, whiche is aboue it and thée, for he dwelleth in a mount higher thou art able to dwell. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o can throw downe his thunderbolts vpon thée, and deſtroy thee, ſo that thou ſhalte neuer recouer thy ſelfe agayne. As it is written: If Edom ſay,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.4.</note> we are impoueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but we wil returne and buylde our deſolate places, yet ſayth the Lorde of Hoſtes, they ſhal buyld, but I wil deſtroy it, and they ſhall be called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> border of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and the people with whome the Lorde is angry for euer. Thus ſhall the Edomites be ouerthrowne (ſayth God) notwithſtanding the ſituatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and the loue of their neighbours, and feare of their enimies. Therfore the ſtays wherby they perſuaded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of ſafty is of no force to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet techeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part of this chap. whoſe words ſerue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al the faithful, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we lerne therby,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:21"/> that no power of man is able to reſiſte God, who fighteth for his people. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al Princes and Nations may learne therby not to truſt in any earthly mighte or ſtrength, nor in the ayde of other men that are their confederates. For God is able to alter mens mindes, and to make them deſpiſed that before were eſtéemed and feared. Héere all nations may learne not to put too muche confidence in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of their countrey, be it neuer ſo well fortified. For God is able to bring downe, &amp; to make weake by one meanes or other, thoſe that are of moſte power and ſtrength. It is not the pollicie nor ſtrength of man that ouercommeth in battell, but God, with a great or ſmall companie of men, yea of himſelf without the miniſterie of man, as pleaſeth him. As we are taught by the example of the people in Noes time vtterly deſtroyed with the floud for their diſobedience:<note place="margin">Gen. 7.21.</note> and by the example of the Sodomites,<note place="margin">Ge. 19.24.</note> deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with fire and brimſtone from heauen. By hindering the buylding of Babell toure through the confuſion of the tungs<note place="margin">Gen. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:10210:21"/> of men:<note place="margin">2. Re. 25 9. Luk. 19.43 &amp;. 21.6. Exo. 14.27 Ioſ. 6.20. &amp; 8.19. &amp;. 10.11. &amp;. 12.9 &amp;c. Iud. 7.22. 2. Reg. 19.35. Pſal. 27.1. Pſal. 18.2.</note> by the deſtruction of the great ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Ieruſalem, and by the victories that Moſes had ouer Pharao, that Ioſua had ouer the Cananites, that Gedeon and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iudges, that Ezechias and other godly Princes had ouer their enimies. Therfore king Dauid (notwithſtanding his owne policie and multitude of men) ſayth: I truſt in the Lorde, of whom ſhal I be afrayde? And, the Lorde is my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, my caſtle, my towre, in whome I truſt, my butkler, my ſhielde, and my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. In like maner, all Princes and Nations, vſing ſuch ordinary meanes as God hath appoynted, ought notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to put their chéef truſt in God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe helpe no Prince is able to mainteyne his eſtate, his owne policie is in vayne, his owne power will not helpe him. For God teacheth vs héere by this Prophet, that althoughe we make our dwelling as highe as the ſtarres, yet he is able to ouerthrowe vs, and to bring vs to nothing. It followeth: If <hi>theeues came vnto thee, or nobbers by night, how miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhouldeſt thou he handled? yet woulde
<pb facs="tcp:10210:22"/> they not ſteale onely ſo muche as ſhoulde be ſufficient for them? if grape gatherers ſhoulde come vnto thee, woulde they not leaue ſome little ones? How are the goodes of Eſau ſought out? howe are his treaſures ſpoyled?</hi> This is the thirde parte of the chapter, in the whiche the Prophet ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth by a compariſon the greatneſſe of the miſerie &amp; calamitie that ſhoulde hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto the Edomites. Great ſhould be their miſerie if they ſhoulde be ſpoyled by théeues, for it is no ſmall gréefe to a man to léeſs in one houre that whiche he hath laboured for many yéeres: Muche more ſhall they be ſpoyled of thoſe eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that God will ſende agaynſt them. For théeues wyll leaue ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde them, as landes, reuenues, and houſholde ſtuffe: but their enimies will take all, and will put them out of their houſes, and diſpoſſeſſe them of all their landes: alſo it is a great miſerie to be ſpoyled of their grapes wherevpon the wealth of their countrey dothe ſtande: yet that is not ſo great as this miſerie that ſhall happen vnto them. For the
<pb facs="tcp:10210:22"/> ſpoylers of grapes will leaue ſome raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cales at the leaſt that are vnrype to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour them withall, but the Nations whome God wyll ſende agaynſt them, will leaue nothing, therefore their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie ſhall be vnſpeakable. For this cauſe the Prophet vttereth it by an exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaying: O howe are the goodes of Eſau ſoughte oute, and hys treaſures ſpoyled? As though he ſhould ſay: I am not able to expreſſe howe the Edomites ſhall bée ſpoyled: yet thys is the leaſte parte of their miſerie, that is more whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che followeth. <hi>All the men that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate wyth thee, haue drye o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee to the borders, the men that were all peace wyth thee, haue deceyued thee, they haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayled agaynſt thee, they that haue had mayntenance by thee, ſhall layd ſnare in thy waye to catche thee, he ſhall not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it.</hi> They ſhall not onely be ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (ſaythe the Prophete) but alſo they ſhall be driuen out of their countrey: yea and that by thoſe in whome they tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, of whom they looked for ayde, with whom they were confederate, &amp; ſo foorth.
<pb facs="tcp:10210:23"/> And this the Prophet vttreth in the time paſt, ſignifying that it is as certayne, as though it were alreadie paſt. And he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth moreouer that this miſerie ſhal come vnto them vpon the ſodayne, ſo that they ſhall not perceyue it: and therefore it is like to be muche greater than if they had foreſéene it. For a Prince that knoweth of his enimies comming, may leuye an armie agaynſt him, and ſo perhaps with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande him, or make ſome other ſhift for him ſelfe: But the Edomites are bereft of this helpe, for they ſhall not perceyue the miſerie that is towards them, before it come, and therfore through their ſoden oppreſſion they are likely to be handled the more miſerably. Agaynſt this it might be obiected: that it is not likely that they ſhoulde be ignorante of that whiche ſhould happen vnto them, ſéeing there are among them ſo many wiſe men, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graue Senators, that coulde foreſée daunger to come. Vnto this God anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by his Prophet as followeth: <hi>Shall not I at that day (ſayth the Lorde) euen cut off from Edom the wiſe men, and vtterly
<pb facs="tcp:10210:23"/> take away vnderſtanding from the mounte of Eſau? Yea moreouer, the courage of thy mightie captaynes (O Teman) ſhall be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, bicauſe euery man ſhall be cut off from the mount of Eſau by ſlaughter.</hi> They ſhal not perceyue or foreſee the daunger at hande (ſayth God) for he wil deſtroy their wiſe Senatours, and take away all men of vnderſtanding from amongſt them. This is a great calamitie, yet he will not onely do this, but alſo he will diſmay, yea and ſlay all their mightie captaynes, ſo that there ſhall be none lefte able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende them. This is taught by the name of <hi>Teman,</hi> whiche was the chiefe citie, and the moſt ancient Dukedome in Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mea, ſo named of <hi>Teman,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of Elephas, Eſaus firſt ſonne.<note place="margin">Gen. 36.15.</note> How their mightie captaynes ſhall be diſmayde, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie declareth, ſaying:<note place="margin">Ier. 49.22.</note> Their heart ſhal be as the heart of a woman with trauell: that is, ful of ſorrow, always lamenting, continually looking for to periſhe. The cauſe of this ſorrowe is the vtter deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Inhabitantes, which vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable miſerie vttered by our Prophet in
<pb facs="tcp:10210:24"/> one worde, is more at large declared by Ieremie in theſe words:<note place="margin">Ier. 49.11.</note> There ſhall be none left to ſay: leaue thy fatherleſſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with me, I wil preſerue them aliue, and let thy widowes truſt in me. As in the ouerthrowe of Sodome and of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morra, and the places neare about (ſayth the Lorde) no man ſhall dwell there, neither ſhal the children of men remaine in it,<note place="margin">Eze. 25.13.</note> So ſhall Edom be. And Ezechiell ſayth: Thus ſayth the Lorde Iehoua, I will ſtretche out my hande vpon Edom, and will deſtroy man and beaſt out of it. This is the great calamitie that God ſayth ſhall come vpon the Edomites: they ſhall be ſpoyled of al their goods, euen to their bid treaſures and moſte precious Iewels, and not that onely, but alſo they ſhall be driuen out of their countrey, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne deſtruction ſhall come vpon them vnwares,<note place="margin">Ez. 35.1. &amp;c.</note> they ſhall all be deſtroyed, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe and wiſe, weake &amp; ſtrong, ſmall and great, poore and riche, man &amp; beaſt. This is the thirde parte of the chapter, whiche (as the former) ſo this ſerueth for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of the faythfull, and correction of
<pb facs="tcp:10210:24"/> the wicked perſecuters of Gods people. For this is the ende &amp; purpoſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, to comfort the Iſraelites béeing in captiuitie, and to diſmay the Edomites their deadly enimies. And what ſoeuer ſerueth for their conſolation, is a general conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for all afflicted Chriſtians that call vpon God, and put their truſt in him. And what ſoeuer ſerueth to diſmay the Edomites, is a generall correction of all wicked perſons that afflict Gods people. For in the deliuerance of the Iſraelites, is declared the goodneſſe of God towards all men: for the goodneſſe of God is one, for God is one, &amp; his goodneſſe is immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And in the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Edomites is ſhewed the iuſtice of God towards all men, for the iuſtice of God is alwayes one, for God is one, and his iuſtice is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable. Therefore I ſay theſe words of the Prophet ſerue for the vſe of all men, for the comforte of the godly, and reprofe of the wicked. They are a ſharpe cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or threatning agaynſt all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuters of the Chriſtians, wherby in the miſerie and calamitie of the Edomites,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:25"/> the Prophet deſcribeth the lamentable ſtate of all that do obſtinately ſet them ſelues agaynſt God and his people. They ſhall be conſtrayned to forgoe all their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches whatſoeuer, their confederates and aliance ſhall perſecute them, and ſéeke their vtter deſtruction, their wiſedome ſhall fayle them, their wiſe men ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fooles, and their ſtrong men ſhall be made weake, no wiſedome nor ſtrength ſhall be able to preuayle agaynſt God. Whereby we are taught that whiche the Prophet Dauid ſayth: it is better to truſt in God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.8.</note> than to truſt in man: it is better to truſt in God, than to truſt in Princes. For man is mutable, but God is immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: the wiſdome of man &amp; his ſtrength fayleth, but the wiſdome and ſtrength of God is aboue all, and endureth for euer, wherby he confoundeth the wiſdome and ſtrength of man, eſpecially of thoſe that reſiſt him, and afflicte his people. A nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble example héereof are the inhabitantes of Ieruſalem in the Apoſtles time, who perſecuted both them and Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour vnto the death, therefore they were
<pb facs="tcp:10210:25"/> miſerably handled, they were not onely ſpoyled of al their ſubſtance, but alſo moſt lamentably deſtroyed, although they had many forwarnings therof, yet they could not perceyue it. They interpreted all things for them that made againſt them, ſo was their wiſedome confounded, and they in the ende vtterly deſtroyed. But we néede not go vnto Ieruſalem for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, we haue examples at home at our owne doores: we néede not goe vnto the Apoſtles time for examples, for wée haue examples of our owne time, in the memorie of vs that are aliue, of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere iuſtice of God towards the enimies of him and his people in the ouerthrowe of the religious houſes of Monkes and Friers, a moſt wicked kinde of men, who had great abundance of precious Iewels and treaſures, they were ſpoyled of all, yea they were diſparſed, and their houſes ouerthrowne, they that were counted the wiſeſt of all men, could not foreſée it, and although ſome of them did foreſée it, yet they could not preuent it. They which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had ſubdued vnto their obedience
<pb facs="tcp:10210:26"/> kings &amp; Emperours could not withſtand it. Their wiſe men were cut off, and the courage of their mightie captaynes was abated. Many finde much fault that their goodly buyldings are decayed, but ſuche men haue not a right opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, ſuch men find fault with the wiſdome &amp; iuſtice of the Lorde. They do not vnderſtand the ſaying of the Prophet Amos:<note place="margin">Amos. 3.6.</note> there is no miſerie that hapneth vnto the citie <hi>of the wicked,</hi> but God ſendeth it. If God did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his owne citie &amp; temple that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to be buylded, whiche was the moſt ſumptuous buylding in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, how could he ſuffer the houſes of them to ſtande, which were not onely diſſembling Hypocrites (as were the Inhabitantes of Ieruſalem) but alſo manyfeſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, moſte filthy adulterers, Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, Théeues, and Murtherers? It muſte needes bée that their buyldings ſhoulde ſtinke in the ſighte of God, and that they ſhoulde ſtirre vp his wrathe to ouerthrowe their godly houſes, leauing onely the rubbiſhe and ſome olde walles for a memorie (as he dyd the ſalte ſtone
<pb facs="tcp:10210:26"/> of Lots wyfe, and the barenneſſe of the countrey of Sodome) for a remembrance vnto the poſteritie, that when the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall aſke their fathers what hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes theſe were, they maye aunſwere: Héere dwelled certayne men of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite Religion, forſakers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſte, and followers of their owne traditions, Idolaters, adulterers, théeues and murtherers. For their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde wickedneſſe the wrath of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God was prouoked agaynſt them, he therefore ſuffereth the Diuell to ſet them at diſcorde among them ſelues, he cauſed their owne companie to bewray their adulterie, Sodomitrie, and their craftie conueyaunce aboute their Imagerie, ſeruyng vnto Idolatrie, whereby he ſpoyled them, diſpearſed them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrewe their coſtly buyldings. Thus God dealed wyth theſe men. And why? The cauſe followeth in the Prophet: <hi>For the cruell ſpoyling of thy brother Iacob, thou ſhalte bee put to ſhame and confuſion, yea thou ſhalt periſhe for euer.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10210:27"/> The crueltie of the Edomites in ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Gods people, was the cauſe why he would ſo gréeuouſly puniſhe them, whoſe wickedneſſe the Prophet amplifieth by putting them in minde of their conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie with the Iſraelites. It is great wickedneſſe, and deſerueth great puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at Gods hande, if they that are not alied do deale cruelly the one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: much more haynous in the ſight of God is the crueltie of brethren one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another. The Iſraelites and Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites were brethren, for they came of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell and Edom, the ſonnes of Iſaac, of whom they had their names, therefore the Edomites were nearer in bloud vnto the Iſraelites than any other nation: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they were partly both of one religion, for they had bothe receyued the couenant of circumciſion, whiche God had giuen vnto their father Abraham, whiche God called his couenant, bicauſe it was a ſeale of that couenant that he made with hys children the Iſraelites, who onely were his people, for as muche as they onely had receyued the couenant it ſelfe. That
<pb facs="tcp:10210:27"/> is to ſay, the promiſe, or the worde of God preached, whereby God offereth him ſelfe vnto vs as vnto children. If we receyue the ſéede of Gods worde, and like good grounde bring foorth fruite, then we are in déede the children of God. But the word was not offred vnto the Edomites, therefore God refuſed them to be his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for among Gods elect theſe two can not be ſeparated, the worde and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. Notwithſtanding the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites were brethren to the Iſraelites ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſhe: therfore the greater was their wickedneſſe in afflicting them, which was the cauſe of their owne cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. But leaſt they ſhould excuſe them ſelues, and ſay: it was the Babylonians and not they, that did ſo cruelly handle the Iſraelites, the Prophet addeth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>At what tyme thou ſtoodeſt a loofe off, at what tyme ſtrangers caried away his ſubſtance, and aliants entred into his gates, and caſt lots vpon Ieruſalem, then thou waſt euen as one of them.</hi> This is it that the Prophet ſayth: although the Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were the chiefe doers, yet the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites
<pb facs="tcp:10210:28"/> were not voyde of faulte, for they brake league with the people of God, they denyed them ayde, they tooke part with the enimies, entered the Citie wyth them, and caſt lottes with them for the deciſion of the ſpoyle: they carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their ſubſtaunce, and in all poynts ſhewed them ſelues their deadly eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Thus the Prophet putteth away their excuſe, and that they maye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the leſſe excuſable, he rehearſeth particularly their faultes, as followeth: <hi>But thou ſhouldeſt not haue beholden the daye of thy brother, the daye in the whiche he was caried into exile, neyther ſhouldeſt thou haue laughed at the inhabitants of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huda, in the day of their deſtruction, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhouldeſt thou haue triumphed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them in the daye of their affliction. Thou ſhouldeſt not haue entered intoo the gates of my people, in the day of their deſtruction, neyther ſhouldeſt thou then haue beholden his miſerie in the day of his deſtruction, neyther ſhouldeſt thou haue layde handes vpon his ſubſtance in the day of his deſtruction. Neither ſhouldeſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:10210:28"/> haue ſtande in the bywayes to ſlay thoſe that otherwiſe had eſcaped, neyther ſhouldeſt thou haue taken priſoners thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned of them in the daye of affliction.</hi> Héere in telling them what they ſhould not haue done, the Prophet openeth vnto them the haynouſneſſe of their faulte by degrées. The firſt is, they did behold with a certayne pleaſure the miſerie of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites. The nature of true friends is to be gréeued when they ſée one an other in miſerie. It was not only no gréefe to the Edomites to ſée the Iſraelites afflicted, but alſo they did laugh at them. Secondly they did triumph ouer them, and (as the words do ſounde) did ſpeake with open mouth agaynſt them, and when they had entred their gates with the enimies, and ſpoyled their ſubſtance, they did ſlay ſome of them, and other ſome they tooke pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. This was the crueltie of the Edomites agaynſt Gods people, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were not accepted of God, as his children, yet he ſuffereth them quietly to enioy their ciuill eſtate in this lyfe, vntill their crueltie was come to the full.
<pb facs="tcp:10210:29"/> So he ſuffereth all reprobates to enioy their eſtate in this lyfe for a tyme, as he did the poſteritie of Cayn, whome at the laſt he deſtroyed by water, ſo he ſuffered the Sodomites to liue voluptuouſly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres, whom in the ende he deſtroyed by fire and brimſtone from heauen. He ſuffered Pharao king of Egypt to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a long time in proſperous eſtate, and afterwarde drowned him and his great armie in the Sea. He ſuffered the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites to triumphe ouer other Nations, and at the length gaue the Iſraelites vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie ouer them, vntill their eſtate was quite ouerthrowne: So God ſuffereth many Princes and Nations to liue qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly for a time, vntill their wickedneſſe be at the full, and then he cutteth them off aſ well in this worlde, as in the world to come. So he did cut off the Edomites for their crueltie towards their brethren: whereby we are taught brotherly loue, and to auoyde iniurious dealing one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, God hath ioyned vs all in one brotherhood, in the confeſſion of one fayth, of one truthe, of one religion, of
<pb facs="tcp:10210:29"/> one Chriſtianitie, and hathe made vs the children by adoption of one father (which is God him ſelfe) and fellowe heires with our Sauiour Chriſte, to the entent we ſhould loue one another: and if we loue as brethren, God will loue vs, and accept vs as his children. Héere for our better inſtruction in this matter, we may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande by the words of the Prophet, that the properties of brotherly loue are not to murther one another, not to ſpoyle one an other, not to triumphe ouer the afflicted, not to reioyce at their miſerie, nor gladly to beholde their calamitie: but rather to be ſory for their heauineſſe, to wéepe with them that wéepe, ſéeking to helpe and ſuccour them, and to delyuer them out of aduerſitie, of what countrey or nation ſo euer they be. The children of God had not reſpecte to countreys, bloud or ſuch like, knowing this, that they haue all one father, and one countrey in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. They that do otherwiſe, or are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe affected, ſhall be gréeuouſly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, they ſhall drinke of the ſame cuppe that they haue giuen to other men, which
<pb facs="tcp:10210:30"/> the Prophet teacheth vs by the wordes following, in that he ſayth: <hi>For the day of Iehoua is at hand vpon all Nations, euen as thou haſt done, it ſhall be done vnto thee: thy miſcheeuous dealing ſhall returne vpon thy owne pate.</hi> For the vnderſtanding of theſe words we haue to conſider what the day of the Lord is, it is a day of afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and great calamitie, a day of muche ſorow &amp; heauineſſe vnto the wicked, but a day of excéeding ioy and gladneſſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worſhippers of God. The Prophet Eſay ſpeaking of the ſame daye, ſayth: <hi>Houle you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>for the daye of the Lorde is at hand, it ſhall come as a deſtroyer from the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, therfore al hands ſhal be weakened, and all mens hearts ſhall melt, and they ſhall be afrayde, anguiſhe and ſorrowe ſhall take them, and they ſhall haue payne as a woman that trauelleth, euery one ſhall be amaſed at his neighbour. Beholde the day of the Lorde commeth cruell, with wrath and fierce anger, to lay the lande waſte, and he ſhall deſtroy ſinners out of it. For the ſtarres of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the planets thereof ſhall not gyue their lighte, the ſunne ſhall bee darkened
<pb facs="tcp:10210:30"/> in his going foorth, and the Moone ſhall not cauſe hir light to ſhine: and I will viſite the wickedneſſe vpon the worlde, and their iniquitie vpon the wicked, and I will cauſe the arrogancie of the proude to ceaſe, and will caſt downe the pride of tyrantes.</hi> Alſo the Prophet Ezechiell ſayth:<note place="margin">Eze. 30.3.</note> 
               <hi>The day of the Lorde is at hande, a cloudy day, and it ſhall be the time of the heathen.</hi> And the Prophet Ioell ſayth: <hi>Alas for the day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel. 1.15. &amp;. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>for the day of the Lord is at hande, and it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as a deſtruction fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the almightie. The day of the Lord is great, &amp; very terrible, who can abide it?</hi> Finally the Prophet Zopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſayth:<note place="margin">Zoph. 1.14</note> 
               <hi>The great day of the Lorde is neare, it is neare, and haſteth greatly, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the voyce of the day of the Lorde. The ſtrong man ſhall crye there bitterly: that day is a day of wrath, a day of trouble and heauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a day of deſtruction and deſolation, a day of obſcuritie and blackneſſe, a day of cloudes and darkneſſe, a day of the trumpet and alarme, againſt the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g cities, &amp; agaynſt the highe toures, and I will bring diſtreſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, and they ſhal walk like blind men, bicauſe they haue ſinned agaynſt the Lorde,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:31"/> and their bloud ſhall be poured out as duſt, and their fleſh as the dung: Neither their ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer nor their golde ſhall be able to delyuer them in the day of the Lords wrath, but the whole lande ſhall be deuoured by the fire of his ielouſie. For he ſhall make euen a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die riddance of all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwell in the land.</hi> By theſe words of the Prophetes it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that the day of the Lorde brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth moſt miſerable deſtruction vnto the wicked, whiche Abdias ſayth ſhall come vpon all nations: that is to ſay: vpon al nations that haue dealt cruelly with the people of God, for ſo in the ſcriptures an vniuerſall ſigne is often times reſtricted. As for example.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.20.</note> Adam called his wyfe Eue, bicauſe ſhe was the mother of euery liuing creature: that is to ſay, ſhe was the mother not of all liuing creatures ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, but of all mankinde, or of euery creature endued with reaſon. And God ſayde,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.3. &amp; .18.18.</note> In Abraham all Nations of the earth ſhall be bleſſed: that is to ſay, all the faythfull of euery Nation, and not all generally without exception.<note place="margin">Gen. 41.57</note> And it is written that euery land came into Egypt
<pb facs="tcp:10210:31"/> for corne, that is to ſay, all that were bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering vpon Egypt, or all that were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with ſcarſitie of corne. Alſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſayth: When I am exalted,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.32.</note> I will draw all men vnto me: that is to ſay, all that do beléeue, and S. Paule ſayth:<note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> All men ſéeke their owne profite: that is to ſay, all men for the moſt parte neglecte their dutie towards God and their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure. So in this place, where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſignifieth, that God will plague all Nations, he vnderſtandeth all thoſe that are enimies vnto the people of God, and not all nations vniuerſally: as it is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by theſe words, As thou haſt done, it ſhall be done vnto thée. For this is the purpoſe of the Prophet to comforte the Iſraelites, whoſe conſolation conſiſteth not in the deſtruction of all nations, but in the ouerthrow of their enimies. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he giueth them to vnderſtande that their enimies ſhall be vtterly deſtroyed, ſaying: <hi>For euen as you haue drunke vpon my holy hill, ſo all nations ſhall drinke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, yea they ſhall drinke, and ſwalowe vp, and they ſhall be as though they had not
<pb facs="tcp:10210:32"/> beene.</hi> By this worde drinke, metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally or figuratiuely is vnderſtanded af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction oftentimes in the ſcriptures, as in theſe words of our Sauiour:<note place="margin">Lu. 26.42.</note> Let this cup paſſe from me, but if it can not paſſe from me, but I muſt néedes drink it, thy wil be done. Heere by drinking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup, he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſuffring of his moſt paynful paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.<note place="margin">Ier. 49.12.</note> Alſo the prophet Ieremie preaching the deſtruction of the Edomites, with Abdias, hath theſe words: <hi>Thus ſayth the Lorde: Beholde they whoſe iudgement was not to drink of the cup haue aſſuredly drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and art thou he that ſhalt eſcape free? Thou ſhalte not goe free, but thou ſhalte ſurely drinke of it. For I haue ſworne by my ſelfe (ſayth the Lorde) that Boſra ſhall be waſt, and for a reproch, and a deſolation, and a curſe, and all the cities thereof ſhal be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall deſolations.</hi> Theſe words do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teache vs, that to drinke figuratiuely ſignifieth to ſuffer affliction. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that he ſayth in the perſon of God, euen as you that are my people haue ben afflicted in your owne countrey, which I haue choſen as a peculiar place for my
<pb facs="tcp:10210:32"/> ſelfe to be worſhipped in: ſo all nations that haue afflicted you, ſhall be plaged, yea they ſhall be miſerably ſcourged, and brought to perpetuall deſolation. Thus the Prophete endeth the firſt chapter of his propheſie, whiche concerneth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Edomites, nowe he deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the felicitie and proſperitie of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites: <hi>But vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mount Sion there ſhal be ſaluation, and it ſhal be holy: and the houſe of Iacob ſhall recouer their poſſeſsions. And the houſe of Iacob ſhall be a fyre, and the houſe of Ioſeph a flame, and the houſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau as ſtubble, and they ſhall kindle among them, and conſume them, and there ſhall be none left of the houſe of Eſau, for Iehoua hath ſpoken it.</hi> Sion is the hill vpon the whiche Ieruſalem was buylded, and is taken for the whole countrey of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites. They ſhall be deliuered (ſaythe the prophet) they ſhal recouer their poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and alſo deſtroy their enimies euen as fire doth conſume ſtubble. For therfore are the Iſraelites likened vnto fire, &amp; the Edomites to ſtubble, to declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſodayne deſtruction, that God ſhall ſende vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:10210:33"/> poſteritie of Eſau, by the hands of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Ieruſalem. Which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ezechiel expreſſeth in playne words ſaying: <hi>I will execute my iudgement vpon Edom by the hande of my people Iſraell, and they ſhall do in Edom according to my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and according to my indignation, and they ſhall knowe my vengeance, ſayth the Lorde God.</hi> Thus God threatneth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the Edomites, but the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites ſhall flouriſhe, as in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it is declared.<note place="margin">Eze. 25.14.</note> 
               <hi>And they ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the Southe ſide of mounte Eſau, and the champion countrey of the Philiſtines, and they ſhall poſſeſſe the feelden countrey of Ephraim, and the feelden countrey of Samaria, and Beniamin ſhal poſſeſſe Gilead.</hi> Héere the Prophet ſheweth the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites how their dominion ſhall be enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. The ſouth ſide of Idumea or of mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Seir is the furtheſt parte of the countrey from Iſraell. This is it therefore that is giuen them to vnderſtande, that they ſhal inhabite not onely their owne countrey, but alſo the countrey of the Edomites, and the Philiſtines, and Beniamin,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:33"/> whoſe habitation is in the weſt, ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe Gilead, which is in the Eaſt: that is to ſay, the Iſraelites ſhall haue dominion from the weſt to the Eaſt, and from the North to South, which in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is further declared: <hi>And they of this hoſt of the Iſraelites, that are in captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie among the Cananites, ſhall poſſeſſe vnto Sarephath, and they of Ieruſalem that are in captiuitie in Sephared, ſhall poſſeſſe the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the South. And there ſhal come vp in mount Sion ſauiours, to giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce agaynſt the mount of Eſau, and Iehoua ſhal haue the kingdome.</hi> That is to ſay, the Iſraelites dominion ſhall be from the South to the North, and from the North to the South, from the one ende of the countrey to the other. For the Cananites dwelled in the South countrey, and Sarephath, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called Sarepta, was in the North, ſo was alſo Seraphad, otherwiſe called Boſphorus (according to the iudgement of ſome Interpreters.) This benefite God promiſeth by his Prophet vnto his people, for bringing of whiche thing to paſſe, he vſed the miniſterie of certayne
<pb facs="tcp:10210:34"/> noble men and chiefe captaynes, as Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabell, Nehemias, Eſdras, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who héere are called Sauiours, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God by their hands chiefly ſaued the people. So in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of the Iudges, Oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell and Ehud are called Sauiours,<note place="margin">Iud 3. verſ. 9. &amp; 15.</note> bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were the captaynes, by whoſe meanes the Iſraelites were deliuered from the bondage of their enimies. The like proſperitie God promiſeth héere vnto the ſame people, the which béeing brought to paſſe, the Prophet ſayth, that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall be the Lordes: that is to ſay, the Iſraelites ſhall not onely be reſtored to their countrey, landes, and poſſeſſions, but alſo they ſhall ſerue God, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe him according to his will. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God ruleth all the world, and all natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s perteyne to his kingdome, yet that properly is called the kingdome of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, where men follow their owne luſt, and neglect the worſhip of God: and there is the kingdome of God, where he is truely worſhipped, the Goſpell prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and his lawes obeyed. Where the Lorde is king there is no tyrannie or
<pb facs="tcp:10210:34"/> bondage, but libertie and fréedome, that people that ſerueth the Lord ſhall floriſh, ſhall proſper, and ſhall be bleſſed in this life, and in the life to come, for he is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, therfore his people ſhall be euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Briefly, this is it that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the former wordes giueth vs to vnderſtand, that the children of God ſhall abound both in earthly and heauenly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions. Whereby we are taught to put our truſt in him, for he is able to help vs, to pray vnto him in al our neceſſities, for he is readie &amp; willing to helpe vs, to giue him thanks for his benefites: for great is his goodnes toward vs, to extoll &amp; magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his name, for wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful are his works, to our great profite and commoditie. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, to obey his lawes and ſtatutes, for he ſerueth them that ſerue him: ſo dooing God will ſende vs ſauiours to ſaue vs, and to deliuer vs from our enimies, and the wordes of the Prophete ſhall be verified vpon vs, in that he ſaythe: The kingdome ſhall bée the Lordes. For he ſhall be our kyng for euer, and we his people ſhall be continually garded
<pb facs="tcp:10210:35"/> vnder the ſhadowe of his wings, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes defended from all maner miſerie and calamitie.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I haue opened the ſence and meaning of the Prophet according to the letter, which although for diuers cauſes it is very neceſſarie to be vnderſtanded: yet béeing conſidered of it ſelfe, without any further application of the ſame vnto our ſelues, it is vnfruitfull and vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.6.</note> As the Apoſtle ſayth: the letter kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, but the ſpirite giueth life. Therfore I haue added moreouer vnto the letter, certayne generall leſſons for the inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Chriſtians. Which application of the ſcriptures vnto our ſelues the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle putteth vs in minde of, where he ſayth:<note place="margin">Rom 15.4</note> what ſoeuer things are written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time, they are written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that we through patience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of the Scriptures might haue hope. And as in diuers other places, ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the thirtenth chapter of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Hebrues, he hath giuen vs an example of this interpretation, where the words of the almightie God, ſpoken only
<pb facs="tcp:10210:35"/> vnto Ioſua, and perteyning onely vnto him, according to the letter, are vſed as a generall leſſon for all men, to teach them to put their truſt in God. After that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was dead, God appoynted Ioſua to be ruler of the Iſraelites, and to bring them into the lande of promiſe: and bicauſe he ſhoulde not feare nor be diſmayde, God ſayde vnto him:<note place="margin">Ioſ. 1.5.</note> As I was with my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant Moſes, ſo I will be with thée, I will not fayle thée, nor forſake thée. Vpon theſe words the Apoſtle groundeth this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall doctrine:<note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> Let your conuerſation be without couetouſneſſe, and be content with thoſe things that ye haue. For he hath ſaide: I will not fayle thee, neyther forſake thée. Thus the Apoſtle diſſuadeth vs through diſtruſt of Gods goodneſſe to vexe our ſelues with immorderate care of worldly riches, and the vnlawful meanes to enriche our ſelues, bicauſe God hath ſayde vnto Ioſua: I will not fayle thée, neyther forſake thee: teaching vs therby to apply the holy Scriptures to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, &amp; confirmation of our fayth. Whoſe example I haue followed by adding the
<pb facs="tcp:10210:36"/> morall (as they call it) vnto the letter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet. But beſides this morall, there is alſo in the propheſie conteyned an alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie, concerning the comming of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to iudgement, &amp; our ful redemption by him in deſtroying Antichriſt, &amp; in brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging vs both body &amp; ſoule vnto the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting bleſſedneſſe, which he hath prepared for all the faithfull. For the wordes and works of God are vnſerchable, &amp; do teach vs a great deale more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the letter at the firſt ſight offreth vnto vs. This I ſay, that in the ſcriptures, eſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writings of Moſes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophets there are for the moſt part thrée ſenſes in one text, &amp; according to thoſe diuers ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, thrée diuers interpretations. The firſt is called literal, gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>matical, or hiſtorical: the ſecond, tropological, ethical, or moral: the third allegorical, figuratiue, or myſticall. The literal interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tical &amp; hiſtorical, bicauſe in it nothing elſe is noted, but that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer rules, &amp; the hiſtorie it ſelf in playne meaning gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs to vnderſtande. This alwayes is fyrſt &amp; chiefly to be noted, as the ground &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10210:36"/> foundation of the other interpretations. If we make not a good foundation, that whiche we buyld thereon will be weake: ſo if we do not truely expound the letter of the ſcripture, commonly we ſhal make an vnprofitable moral, and a falſe allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. The bare letter, of the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſpecially, is for the moſt part very profitable and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious to al Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. There are fiue generall vſes &amp; commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the ſcripture, taught of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. Paule in the Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, the .15. chapter,<note place="margin">Rom. 15 4</note> and in the ſeconde Epiſtle to Timothie the third chapt.<note place="margin">2. Ti. 3.16</note> Firſt by it we learne patience in aduerſitie, by it we haue conſolation in perſecution, and are therby encouraged to continue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende in the true worſhip of God, through hope of life euerlaſting: ſecondly we are taught true doctrine as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> articles of our fayth: and thirdly, to improue falſe doctrine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: fourthly by the ſcriptures we lerne to correct our wicked liuing, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and finally we are therby inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in godlineſſe, &amp; in al ſuch things as are
<pb facs="tcp:10210:37"/> acceptable vnto God. All theſe commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities are founde in the literall ſence of the ſcriptures. For what is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable than the very letter of theſe wordes?<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> So God loued the worlde that he gaue his onely begotten ſonne, to the ende, that who ſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſhe, but haue life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.28 Gal. 2.16.</note> And the letter of theſe words: We are iuſtified by fayth without the works of the lawe, doth teache vs the doctrine of iuſtification by fayth, without any deſert of our good works, &amp; alſo doth improue the contrarie. In like maner the letter of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places doth teach other doctrine. And where the Apoſtle ſayth:<note place="margin">Gal. 5.19.</note> The workes of the fleſhe are manifeſt, which are adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnclenneſſe, wantonneſſe, Idolatrie, witchcraft, hatred, debate, emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, wrath, contentions, ſeditions, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, enuy, murthers, dronkenneſſe, gluttonie, and ſuche like, whereof I tell you before, as alſo I haue tolde you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they which do ſuch things ſhall not inherite the kingdome of God. But the fruite of the ſpirite is loue, ioy, peace,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:37"/> long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, fayth, méekeneſſe, temperancie, agaynſt ſuche there is no lawe. The very letter of theſe words ſerueth to correct and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs in godlineſſe. So commodious is the bare letter of the holy Scriptures, and the morall therof (which is to gather out of the letter ſome good leſſon for our inſtruction) is no leſſe profitable. For all the miracles of our ſauiour Chriſt, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the letter and hiſtorie, they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to the commoditie of thoſe that were healed by him, ſo they may be morally interpreted to our comforte, and to the confirmation of our fayth that are nowe liuing. For by his goodneſſe thereby ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto other men, we haue an euident argument of his readineſſe to helpe vs, when ſoeuer we in like ſort do ſéeke helpe at his hands: ſo that we haue no cauſe to miſtruſt his goodneſſe, nor to ſéeke helpe elſe where, of Saincts and Angels, that are no ſauiours. His miracles alſo doe teache vs his Diuinitie, they teache vs that he is Chriſt the ſauiour of the world, and do improue the contrarie doctrine, as
<pb facs="tcp:10210:38"/> our Sauiour witneſſeth in the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.4. Iohn. 5.36. &amp; .14.11.</note> Moreouer all the examples of godly men ſerue for our inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and the examples of the wicked with their puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſerue for our correction. After this ſort the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paule expoundeth the manyfolde plages of the Iſraelites in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.6</note> and according to the moral ſenſe, applieth them vnto vs, teaching vs by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to auoyde their wickedneſſe. Finally, in the ſcriptures, beſides the letter and the moral, there is a true and a profitable al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorie, type, figure, or myſterie. As for example:<note place="margin">Gen. 22.9.</note> the offering of Iſaac vpon the aulter, to be ſlayne by the hands of his father, as God had commaunded, whiche as according to the letter, it was a triall of Abrahams fayth, and alſo an inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs (whiche is the morall) teaching vs to obey Gods commaundementes in all poyntes, and to beléeue hys promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, although they ſéeme neuer ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to mans reaſon: So in that Iſahac was layde vpon the aulter readie to be ſlayne, and then by the voyce of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, and (as it were) rayſed from
<pb facs="tcp:10210:38"/> death to life agayne, he was a type and figure of our Sauiour Chriſt, teaching vnto Abraham and his poſteritie ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the offering of Chriſt vpon the croſſe, and by his reſurrection from death. Alſo Ioſeph beeing ſolde by his brethren vnto ſtraungers, caſt into priſon,<note place="margin">Gen. 37.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gen. 39. &amp;. 41. &amp; .42. &amp; .47.</note> &amp; after made ruler of the countrey of Egypt, where he prouided foode, and alſo a fruitefull lande for his father and brethren to dwell in (as it declareth Gods wonderfull power and goodneſſe towards him, and alſo the ſtate of Gods children in this life, béeing firſt by affliction thruſt downe (as it were) into hell, and after exalted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen: So it was a fygure of oure Sauiour: fyrſt ſolde and deliuered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the handes of the Gentiles, euen by hys owne countrey menne, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and afterwards of hys Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and glorification, by hys Aſcention into heauen, where of his mercie, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to our deſeruing, he hathe prouided for vs a perpetuall reſte and habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for euer, euen for as manye as
<pb facs="tcp:10210:39"/> come vnto him for ſuccour.<note place="margin">Ex. 1. &amp; .14.</note> Moreouer the bondage of the Iſraelites in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and their deliuerance through the deſtruction of Pharao in the red ſea: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it declareth the power and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God towards them, and the ſtate of his children before rehearſed: it was a type of our bondage through ſinne, death, hell, and the diuell, and of our deliuerance from the ſame by our ſauiour Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying our enimies, and bringing vs vnto euerlaſting felicitie. Likewiſe the Paſcall lambe receyued euery yere,<note place="margin">Exo. 12.3.</note> bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a lambe without blemiſh, (the bloud wherof was ſprinkled vpon the poſtes of the doore, ouer which the deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell paſſed, hurting none in the houſe where the bloud was ſprinkled) This Lambe, I ſay, in an allegorie ſignifieth our ſauiour Chriſt, béeing without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhe and ſpotte of ſinne, whoſe bloud ſprinkled vpon the poſtes of our hearts by fayth, deliuereth vs from euerlaſting deſtruction. We are taught this allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall expoſition of the Paſcall Lambe by Iohn Baptiſt, where poynting vnto our
<pb facs="tcp:10210:39"/> ſauiour Chriſt, he ſayth:<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.29.</note> Behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe of God that taketh away the ſinne of the world. Alſo the Apoſtles Paule and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, do liken our Sauiour vnto the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lambe, ſaying:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.7. 1. Pet. 1.19.</note> Chriſt our Paſſeouer is ſacrificed for vs, and we are redéemed with the precious bloud of Chriſt, as of a Lambe vndefiled, and without ſpot. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this figuratiue and myſticall interpretation, the Apoſtle expoundeth the hiſtorie of Abrahams two wiues and their children:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> where he playnly poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at our aduerſaries the Papiſts, who ſéeke iuſtification by their owne works, and do perſecute thoſe, which according to Gods promiſe, do ſéeke life by faythe in Chriſt: whoſe miſerable ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Apoſtle ſheweth, prouing by an allegorie, that all they which ſéeke iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, by the bondage of the lawe, ſhall be caſt out of the lande of promiſe with the bonde woman and hir ſonne, and ſhal not inherite the euerlaſting kingdome of God with his children, that are frée, and do ſeeke ſaluation throughe fayth in his promiſe. Héere it is euident that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb facs="tcp:10210:40"/> teacheth vs to expound the ſcriptures, not literally onely, but alſo allegorically, myſtically, or figuratiuely. So he expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thoſe words:<note place="margin">Deu. 25.4. 1. Cor. 9.9.</note> Thou ſhalt not moſell the Oxe that treadeth out the corne. In like maner the rocke in the wilderneſſe, out of the which water flowed to ſatiſfie the thirſt of the Iſraelites:<note place="margin">Exo. 17.6.</note> beſides that, it declareth Gods power and prouidence for his children béeing in diſtreſſe, it prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the graces and giftes of God that flow out of our ſauiour Chriſte vnto all that beléeue in him. For ſo the Apoſtle expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.3</note> where he ſayth: Our fathers dyd eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and dyd drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke, for they dranke of the ſpirituall rocke that follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed them, and the rock was Chriſt. And the ſerpent that Moſes ſet vp at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God,<note place="margin">Num. 21.8.</note> beſides the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous healing of thoſe that were bytten with fyry Serpents, teacheth bothe the Iſraelites and vs to lift vp the eyes of our fayth vnto our Sauiour lifted vp vpon the croſſe, ſéeking deliuerance by him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deadly ſting of the Serpent the diuel.
<pb facs="tcp:10210:40"/> For that braſen ſerpent was a figure of our ſauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.14.</note> as he himſelfe expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it in the Goſpell. Moreouer where Moſes telleth the people that God wyll rayſe vnto them a Prophete like vnto him ſelfe, euen of their brethren,<note place="margin">Deu. 18.15.</note> vnto whom they ſhould herken: the letter tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs nothing elſe but that Ioſua ſhould gouerne the Iſraelites, and bring them into the lande that God had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them. But the holy Ghoſt in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Ioſua (whoſe name ſignifieth a ſauiour) teacheth vs that Chriſt is our ſauiour, who bringeth vs into the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting reſt promiſed vnto all the faithfull, for ſo the Apoſtle Peter expoundeth the words of Moſes.<note place="margin">Act. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Alſo euen as the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bage of the Iſraelites in Egypte, and their peregrinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the wilderneſſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is playnly expreſſed by the letter) doth repreſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in this life, béeing ful of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the land of Canaan promiſed vnto Gods people, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they had a great conqueſt ouer the wicked, &amp; after quietly enioyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey (beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gods excéeding
<pb facs="tcp:10210:41"/> power and excellent benefites beſtowed vpon them) doth repreſent vnto vs the euerlaſting reſt in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we ſhall enioy whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almightie God hath deſtroyed all the wicked vpon the earth. So the Apoſtle expoundeth the wordes of the prophet Dauid, who concerning the ſame matter,<note place="margin">Pſa. 95.10.</note> ſayth: Fortie yéeres long was I gréeued with this generation, &amp; ſayde: It is a people that doth erre in their hearts, for they haue not knowne my ways, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom I ſware in my wrath,<note place="margin">Nu. 14.23</note> that they ſhould not enter into my reſt. Whiche words written bothe in the lawe and in the Prophet, according to the letter, doe ſhew the reſt of the Iſraelites in the land of Canaan, but according to the allegorie, they teache al the faythful the euerlaſting reſt by Chriſt in heauen.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.9.</note> But for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declaration of this double, and triple ſence of the Scripture, and the manifolde commoditie thereof,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 18.11. &amp; .19.11. &amp; 23.8. &amp; .26 2. &amp;c. 2. Sam. 5.3</note> let vs conſider the hiſtorie of Dauid perſecuted by Saule, and after exalted to the kingdome of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. As touching the letter euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath read the bookes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel
<pb facs="tcp:10210:41"/> doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that Dauid was liuing about a thouſand yeres befere the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our Sauiour in the fleſh, &amp; that béeing perſecuted of king Saule; he was diuers times in danger of death, from the which God did wonderfully deliuer him, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deliuered Sauls into his hands, but he would not lay ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vpon him vnto death. And when tidings was brought him that Saule was dead,<note place="margin">2. Sa. 1.15.</note> he executed the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as a murtherer, bicauſe he confeſſed that he had ſlayn him.<note place="margin">2. Sa. 2.4.</note> Then he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed king, and after that he was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the kingdome,<note place="margin">2. Sa 11. ver 4. &amp; .17.</note> he committed adultrie with Bethſabe, and cauſed hir huſband to be ſlayne, and did other things diſpleaſant vnto God, for the whiche he was gréeuouſly puniſhed. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of the letter. As touching the morall, we learne by Dauids fall, and the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his wickedneſſe, to looke circumſpectly vnto our ſelues, and to feare the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God for our iniquities. We learne by his whole life, that affliction is a good ſcholemaſter vnto godlineſſe, in that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayneth our carnall luſtes, and kéepeth
<pb facs="tcp:10210:42"/> downe our fleſh, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maketh vs forget the lawes of god: for Dauid in aduerſitie would not ſlay Saul the king,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 24.7. &amp; .26.9.</note> when he was deliuered into his hands, although he were his deadly eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, giuing vs an enſample of our duetie towards our Prince, ſo narowly did he looke vnto his pathes, but in proſperity he neglected Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; ſwarued from his ordinances by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, murther, &amp; other offences. Wherby we are taught that proſperitie is a ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place to ſtand vpon. It is like an high ſtéepe mountayne, narrow in the top, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the which a man ſtanding is in danger of euery wind to be blowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down, &amp; to break his neck, except he hold faſt by ſome trée, or hide him ſelfe vnder ſome buſh, or ſuch like: ſo in proſperity we are in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery aſſault of the fleſh, world, &amp; diuel, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we hold faſt by a true faith in Chriſt, who is a ſure ſtay, &amp; our only ſtay both in proſperitie &amp; aduerſitie: without who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we can not be ſafe, neither in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of honor &amp; welth, nor in the valley of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For it may be, that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes of much rain,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:42"/> the valley may be ouerflowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with water, &amp; they drouned that dwel in it, vnleſſe they ſaue them ſelues by a bote, or ſuche other meanes: ſo in aduerſitie we are in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to be ouerwhelmed with the waues of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, &amp; to be prouoked to forſake God, excepte we cleaue faſt vnto Chriſt, by a liuely fayth: who is our only arke of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Therfore Dauid doth not ſay: I truſt in the valley, but I truſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.1.</note> wherfore do they ſay vnto my ſoule: flye vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mountains. Thus much of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral in the hiſtory of Dauid. There is in it alſo an allegory or myſtery, prefiguring our ſauiour Chriſt: which we lerne by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets, Ezechiel &amp; Hoſhea, where God ſpeaketh in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this ſort:<note place="margin">Eze. 34.23 &amp; .37.24.</note> I will ſet a ſhepherd ouer my ſhéepe, &amp; he ſhall feede them, euen my ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Dauid, he ſhal féede them, &amp; he ſhall be their ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, &amp; I the Lord wil be their God, and my ſeruant Dauid ſhall be the Prince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, he ſhall be king ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and they ſhal haue one ſhepheard, and my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant Dauid ſhal be their Prince for euer.<note place="margin">Eze. 37.25. Hoſ. 3.5.</note> The children of Iſraell ſhall turne and
<pb facs="tcp:10210:43"/> ſéeke the Lorde their God, &amp; Dauid their king, and ſhall feare the Lorde &amp; his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in the later days. Theſe Prophets Hoſhea and Ezechiel, liued the one thrée hundred yeres, &amp; the other foure hundred yeres after Dauid. Therfore ſéeing they propheſie of a Dauid to come after them in the later dayes, and bicauſe they call him an euerlaſting king (which can not be verified of Dauid literally béeing a mortall man) it is euident that they do meane an other prefigured by Dauid: that is to ſay, our Sauiour, who gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the true Iſraelites: that is to ſay, the elect people of God for euer, who alſo in the Goſpel calleth himſelfe the good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard:<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.11</note> giuing vs to vnderſtand that he is that Dauid, the ſhepheard of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of whome the Prophets do ſpeake. Therfore the hiſtorie of Dauid is myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally expounded thus: Dauid in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, therby brought downe (as I may ſay) vnto hell, dothe ſignifie our Sauiour, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our nature vpon him, and debacing him ſelfe vnto the loweſt degrée, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling him ſelfe vnto the death, euen vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:10210:43"/> death of the croſſe: and Dauid deliuered from his enimies, and placed in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, doth ſignifie our Sauiour riſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, and aſcending vnto heauen, where he is exalted vnto the right hand of God, and gouerneth all the worlde. Thus this hiſtorie may truly be expounded, wherby we may vnderſtande, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, much more is to be conſidered than the letter at the firſt ſight offreth vnto vs. After this ſorte alſo the Apoſtle teacheth vs to expounde the hiſtorie of Salomon, Dauids ſonne.<note place="margin">2. Sa. 7.13.</note> God ſayd vnto Dauid that he would giue him a ſonne, whoſe throne he would eſtabliſh for euer, and he would be his father, and he ſhould be his ſonne: where the letter directeth vs vnto Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,<note place="margin">1. Re. 2.46</note> who then had eſtabliſhed the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnto him ſelfe, when he had put to death thoſe that rebelled againſt him and his father. But the holy Ghoſt in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Salomon, as in a type and figure, teacheth vs that our ſauiour Chriſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſubdued all the enimies of his father and of him ſelfe, ſhall reigne for euer, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly with his faythfull ſeruants that her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:10210:44"/> vnto his lawes, &amp; ſubmit themſelues vnto his gouernment. Vnto this expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtle leadeth vs, where he applieth the words of almightie God vnto our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.4.</note> ſaying: Chriſt is ſo much the more excellent than Angels, as he hath gotten him a more excellent name tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they. For vnto which of the Angels ſaide he at any time,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.7. 2. Sa. 7.14</note> Thou art my ſonne, this day haue I begotten thée? And agayn: I wil be his father, &amp; he ſhall be my ſonne. Therefore ſéeing that the Apoſtle expoundeth the words to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Sauiour, which literally do appertein vnto Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſay that Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was a figure of our ſauiour, &amp; that in the hiſtory of Salomon there is an allegory beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter.<note place="margin">Ionas. 1.17.</note> Likewiſe Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas in the whales belly, &amp; after deliuered by the power of God, was not only an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Gods omnipotent goodneſſe, but alſo a figure of the buriall &amp; reſurrection of our Sauiour:<note place="margin">Mat. 12.40</note> as we are taught by his owne interpretation in the Goſpell. And Hoſhea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet declaring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefites of God towards the Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.1.</note> &amp; their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe for the ſame, reciteth their
<pb facs="tcp:10210:44"/> deliuerance out of Egypt. In whom God ſpeketh thoſe words: out of Egypt I haue called my ſonne. Where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter teacheth vs nothing elſe but the deliuerance of the Iſraelites out of captiuitie: but the holy Ghoſt vnderſtandeth moreouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our ſauiour out of Egypt into his own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Herod. For ſo the Prophets words are expounded in the Goſpel.<note place="margin">Mat. 2.15.</note> Finally the Prophet Ieremy declaring the deliuerance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites out of captiuitie, deſcribeth firſt their gret affliction, ſaying: Thus ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Ier. 31.15.</note> a voyce was herd on high, a mourning and bitter wéeping, Rachell wéeping for hir childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; would not be comforted, bicauſe they wer not. Thus ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, refraine thy voyce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wéeping, &amp; thine eyes from teres, for thy work ſhal be rewarded, ſaith the Lord, &amp; they ſhal come again fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of their enimies. Here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter teacheth vs only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> returning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelits, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity of Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt therby vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites for their Infants,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.18.</note> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herode ſlue at the birth of our ſauiour Chriſt, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt
<pb facs="tcp:10210:45"/> witneſſeth. So I ſay in this Prophet Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias, beſides that hath béene alreadie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we are taught Chriſt, and the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our enimies by him, for he hathe applied the writings of all the Prophets vnto him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Lu. 24.27.</note> when he accompanied the two Diſciples vnto Emaus after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. For S. Luke ſayth that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at Moſes, and at al the Prophets, and interpreted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all the ſcriptures thoſe things that were written of him. And S. Peter ſayth:<note place="margin">Act. 3.24.</note> Al the Prophets fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Samuel and thence foorth, euen as many as haue written, haue foretolde of thoſe dayes: that is to ſay, of the wonderfull workes then wrought in the name of Chriſt, and of his death and reſurrection. Alſo Zachary Iohn Baptiſt father,<note place="margin">Luk 1.70</note> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord God of Iſrael, for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Chriſt our mightie ſauiour, as he had promiſed by the mouth of his holy Prophets that haue bin from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world. Therfore ſéeing that all the Prophets haue foreſpoken of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Chriſt. Abdias alſo, with the reſidue, hath propheſied of him: ſo that in this
<pb facs="tcp:10210:45"/> Prophet we may finde our deliuerance by Chriſt, and conſequently, the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Antichriſt. Which he dothe here firſt teach vs vnder the name of Edom &amp; Eſau. The ſignification of the word Edo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pointeth vs to the perſon, and alſo to the place, where Antichriſt dwelleth. For Edom in the Hebrue tong,<note place="margin">An allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie gathered of the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the worde Edom.</note> ſignifieth red or bloudie. The Biſhop of Rome (which is Antichriſt) ſheweth him ſelfe to be E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that is red and bloudy, both in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde appearance, and alſo in his ſecrete deuiſes, for he and his Cardinals, his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and other his adherents, are clothed in red, the ſeruing men of his Clergie goe in red. This is their colour wherewith they are delighted: So alſo their dooings are red and bloudie. For this is the fyrſt decrée of their ſecret counſel at Trent: Al they that profeſſe the Goſpel, and are eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnto the Church of Rome, ſhall be rooted out, they ſhall be ſlayne, and put to death, their bloud ſhall be ſhed vpon the earth. This is their bloudy decrée which they haue practiſed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter moſt of their power, héer in England, in Scotland, and
<pb facs="tcp:10210:46"/> of late in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and in many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſtendome, as Germany, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Spayne, and Italie: So that they are altogither delighted in bloud, and wil neuer be ſatiſfied. Therefore they maye well be called Edomits, red &amp; bloudy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moreouer not only the ſignification of the worde, but alſo the teſtimonie of diuers ancient writers, leadeth vs to vnderſtand by this name Edo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Antichriſt of Rome, who are perſuaded that he is not onely in outwarde pompe and ſhew, and in déedes an Edomite, but alſo in bloud &amp; kinred, as one that had his beginning of the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites.<note place="margin">Ancient te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies witneſsing that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome is an Edomite, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently Antichriſt.</note> For <hi>Moſes Gerundenſis</hi> writing of the beginning of the Romanes, ſayth: we haue heard in the bookes of the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles of <hi>Ioſeph ben Gorian,</hi> and in other bookes of Antiquities, that Sappho the ſonne of Eliphas, the ſonne of Eſau, the father of the Edomites, prouoked Ioſeph the ſonne of Iacob to warre, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was gouernour of Egypt: In the which war Sappho the Edomite, and his valiaunt captaynes were taken and caried into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, and there committed vnto priſon,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:46"/> where they remayned as long as Ioſeph liued. And when he was dead Sappho fledde away, and went into Campania, and reigned ouer Kittim, at Rome. At the length he was made king ouer all I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, and this was the firſt king of Rome. Alſo <hi>Dauid Kimchi</hi> writing vpon this Prophete, ſayth: The Edomites are nowe ſo mingled among other Nations, that a man can not knowe them from the Ammonites and Moabites, and the people of other Countreys, ſauing that the greater parte of the Edomites hath béene from the beginning of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Rome.<note place="margin">Eſa. 34.6. Ier. 49.7. Lam. 4.21. Eze 25.13.</note> Therefore what ſoeuer the Prophets haue ſpoken of the deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Idumea, in the latter ende of the worlde, they haue ſpoken it agaynſt Rome. For when ſoeuer Rome ſhall be deſtroyed, Iſraell ſhall be deliuered. Thus beſides that theſe writers teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that the Romanes had their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Edomites, <hi>Kimchi</hi> ſaythe, that by the Edomites the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes doe vnderſtande the Romanes. And hée ſaythe moreouer: Abdias
<pb facs="tcp:10210:47"/> propheſieth onely agaynſt Edom, not that externall Edom (as it ſéemeth) but an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: that is to ſay, agaynſt the ſpirituall Edom, the Antichriſt of Rome: whiche was little &amp; deſpiſed in the beginning, but through the pride of his heart, much exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, like an Eagle making his neſt aboue the ſtarres, and rioting vpon the mounte of Sion. Moreouer an other olde writer, the author of the booke called <hi>Seder olam,</hi> that is to ſay, a rehearſall of antiquities, calleth Rome Edom, in theſe words: Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patian (for ſo he termeth Veſpatia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) came and waſted the temple, and caried away many families of the houſe of Dauid, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Spayne, and this was the. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>80.</hi> yeres of Edom, or of the Romanes. Finally Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan the Chaldey paraphraſt, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, where the Prophetes name Edom, in ſtéede therof he nameth Rome. As for example:<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 34.9.</note> The floudes of Edom (ſayth the Prophet) ſhall be turned into pitche. Which words the Paraphraſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting, ſayth: The flouds of Rome ſhal be turned into pitche. And vpon the laſt verſe of this Prophet, he ſayth: And
<pb facs="tcp:10210:47"/> they ſhal folow the ſauiour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mount of Sion, to giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mount of Eſau, and that (ſayth he) is the mount of Rome. Thus it appereth by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of theſe writers, that by the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Edo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is vnderſtanded the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Antichriſt of Rome. This is it therefore, that the Prophet teacheth vs, beſides that hath bin already noted.<note place="margin">The allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Prophet Abdias.</note> That almightie God hath determined to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the perſecuter of his children. The Embaſſadour our ſauiour Chriſt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie ſent, and proclaymeth at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, by the mouth of his Preachers war againſt him, ſaying: vp let vs ariſe againſt Rome vnto battell: let vs with al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gifts that God hath giuen vs, ouerthrowe the foure of Idolatrie and ſuperſtition which Antichriſt hath buylded to deface the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of almightie God: let vs deliuer Gods children out of the dangerous captiuitie &amp; thraldome of ignorance, which bringeth deſtruction of body and ſoule to al that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein. So God by his Prophet threatneth the deſtruction of this Edom, no leſſe than of the other. For (as by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon
<pb facs="tcp:10210:48"/> it may appeare) the ſame cauſe of deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in the one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was in the other: alſo the power &amp; might aſwell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one as of the other, is of late days by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful working of almightie God maruelouſly diminiſhed, &amp; his glory defaced. The Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites were beloued of their neighbours, &amp; feared of their enimies, therefore great was their pride, but they were brought to deſolation by their own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federates: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo it was with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop of Rome, he was beloued of al princes in Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, they reuerenced him as a god, alſo they feared him, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they durſt not ſtir agaynſt him. For what Prince ſoeuer did not in all pointes ſubmit him ſelfe vnto him at his pleſure, he exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated him, diſcharged his ſubiects of obedience, &amp; in the end de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him of his kingdome: for beſides the tranſlating of the Empire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to an other, beſides the depoſing of Hilderike king of France, &amp; diuers other inferiour Princes:<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.13.</note> he exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated &amp; depoſed ſeuen Emperours one after an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: namely Henry the fourth, &amp; Henry the fifth, Frederik the firſt, Philip, Otho,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:48"/> Frederike the ſeconde, and Conradus his ſonne. Therfore great is the pride of his heart: ſo that he exalteth him ſelfe aboue men and Angels, he compareth him ſelfe with the ſunne, and the Emperour with the moone, chalenging vnto him ſelfe ſo muche more excellencie than the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as the ſunne excelleth the moone. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the earth (ſayth he) ſurmounteth the moone ſeuen times, and the ſunne ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth the earth eyght times (whiche béeing multiplied by ſeuen maketh fifty &amp; ſixe) ſo be excelleth the Emperour fifty and ſixe times. Neither is he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tnet with this ſuperioritie ouer the Emperour, but alſo he preferreth him ſelfe before the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in iuriſdiction, knowledge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. This is the pride of his hart, in the which Pope Alexander the thirde of that name, trode vpon the necke of Frederike the Emperour, ſaying this verſe of the Pſalme: Thou ſhalt walk vpon the Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the Aſpe, the yong Lion and the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon ſhalte thou treade vnder thy féete. And Pope Adrian the fourth ſuffered the ſame Emperour to hold his ſtyrup twiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:49"/> and gaue him a ſcoffe for his labour, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did holde the wrong ſtirup. Alſo Pope Gregorie the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th ſuffred Henry the Emperour, the fourth of that name, to ſtande bare foote and bare legged at his gates, with his wife and his childe, thrée dayes &amp; thrée nightes in the middeſt of winter. Such was the pride of his hart which had ſo deceyued him, that he thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght it vnpoſſible that he ſhoulde be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen. But (as it appeareth this day) the Biſhop of Rome is of little reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is deſpiſed of many nations, of whom in times paſt he was feared. The moſte part of his confederates haue forſaken him: as the Polonians, the Tranſſilua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians &amp; Hungarians, many Princes of Germanie, the Princes of Englande and Scotlande, and many men in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys. And it is not to be doubted but that ſhortly by the working of almightie God the words of this Prophet ſhall be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in him: that is to ſay, he ſhall be brought downe to the grounde, he ſhal be ſpoyled of all his treaſures, &amp; vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of all his friends, &amp; cut off from the
<pb facs="tcp:10210:49"/> earth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoden, with al his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. For the day of the Lord is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, a day of tribulation &amp; anguiſh, a day of gret ſorow &amp; heauineſſe,<note place="margin">Zoph. 1.15.</note> a day (as the Prophet Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phony termeth it) of deſolation &amp; deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of obſcuritie &amp; darkneſſe, of cloudes &amp; blackneſſe vnto al the enimies of Gods children.<note place="margin">2. Th. 1.8.</note> The day (I meane) when our Sauiour ſhal come from heauen with his mightie Angels, in flaming fire, rendring vengeance vnto all thoſe that knowe not God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that do not obey the Goſpel of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting perdition, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſence of the Lord, &amp; from the glory of his power. But vpon mount Sion ſhal be ſaluation, the children of God ſhall haue no cauſe to lament,<note place="margin">Reue 21.4</note> when the terrible day of the Lord ſhall come: for that day ſhal be their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance. Then ſhall their enimies weepe and lament, but they ſhall be glad, and ful of ioy: for their ſakes all the wicked ſhal be conſumed as ſtubble with the fire, for God wil ſende his Angels,<note place="margin">Mat. 13. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 41. &amp; 49</note> &amp; they ſhal ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the nations of the worlde before him, and ſhall ſeparate the faythfull from the vnfaythful, as the huſband man ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth
<pb facs="tcp:10210:50"/> the wheat fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tares, &amp; they ſhal binde the tares togither, &amp; caſt them into the fire that neuer ſhal be quenched: but the faithfull which are the wheat, ſhall be gathered into Gods barne: that is to ſay, they ſhal be placed in his kingdome of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ioy, peace, and reſt. And then all principalities &amp; powers béeing ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be able to ſtir againſt God, or agaynſt his ſaincts, which before were deſpiſed, trode vnder foote, &amp; moſt cruelly murthered: but now deliuered out of all miſery, exalted into heauen, and glorified. So that in all poynts, &amp; in all reſpects, the Lorde ſhal rule, he only ſhall be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and glorified, the kingdome ſhall be his. To whom be all prayſe, honor, and glory, world without ende. Amen.</p>
            <p>THus endeth the expoſition of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Abdias, in the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter hath his place and his commendation: that is, the playne meaning of the wordes of the holy Scripture, without any morall or allegoricall expoſition (whiche I call the letter) is profitable to comfort, to teache, to improue, to correct, and to inſtructe in godlyneſſe, whiche is rather to giue lyfe
<pb facs="tcp:10210:50"/> than to kil. Therfore here a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may aſke this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: How is it true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle ſayth: The letter killeth,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.6.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life? for if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter kil, it is hurtfull, if it be hurtful, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is not profitable, as is aforeſaid. Here for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle, firſt it is to be noted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is in one ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a true letter, there is alſo in the ſame ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical &amp; a falſe letter. As for example:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.24</note> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce (ſayth the Apoſtle) in my afflictions for you, &amp; fulfil the reſt of Chriſtes afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in my fleſh, for his bodies ſake, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church. Here by Chriſtes afflictions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, wherof Chriſt is the head. The afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtes afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, bicauſe whatſoeuer the body ſuffreth, the head, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, our fauiour Chriſt is partaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, as appeareth by his own words, where he ſayth: Saule,<note place="margin">Act. 22.7.</note> Saule why per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuteſt thou me? and yet Saule perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not Chriſt in his owne perſon, as the Iewes had done before, but in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans which are members of his body. And where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.5.</note> as the afflictions of
<pb facs="tcp:10210:51"/> Chriſt do abound in vs: ſo our conſolation aboundeth through Chriſt: it is euident that he calleth our afflictions Chriſtes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, both bicauſe we are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of his body, &amp; alſo bicauſe we ſuffer like afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with him for his ſake. Therefore as long as there remaineth one aliue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal ſuffer for Chriſtes ſake, ſo long there remayne behind vnfulfilled ſome of Chriſtes afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which his ſaincts ſuffer for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church and for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of the ſame in the true fayth, that it may continue vnto the ende, &amp; be ſaued. This is the commoditie that we receiue by the ſufferings of them that are perſecuted for Chriſtes ſake, as we learne by the wordes of the Apoſtle, where he ſayth:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.5.</note> Whether we be afflicted, it is for your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is wrought in the induring of the ſame ſuffrings which we alſo ſuffer: or whether we be comforted, it is for your conſolation &amp; ſaluation.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.13 Reue. 2 ver. 7.11.17. &amp;. 26. &amp; ca. 3. ver. 5.12. &amp;. 21. &amp; ca. 21.7.</note> Saluation is wrought (ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle) by enduring afflictions, bicauſe except we ouercome our enimies, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, the world, &amp; the diuel, by continuing ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt vnto the ende, we can not be ſaued. Therfore ſaluation is wrought by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:51"/> not that it is meritorious, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional. If we continue vnto the end in the true worſhip of God, ſuffering al the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are laide vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to withdraw vs from the ſame, there is laide vp for vs in heauen an euerlaſting crowne, which God of his mercy &amp; goodnes will giue vs, and not for the deſert of our owne works. For as God for his promiſe ſake wil giue euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beléeue in him,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.32</note> ſo he requireth at our handes that we confeſſe him before men, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his faythful ſeruants vnto the end, &amp; that we do not ſhrink fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the confeſſion of the Chriſtian faith for any worldy reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. For this cauſe if we indure afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, our ſuffrings do ſerue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as is aforeſaid) both of our ſelues, &amp; of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus (if the true ſenſe &amp; meaning of the Apoſtles wordes may be called a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) it may appere what is the true letter of the former words, recited out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt chap. of the Epiſtle to the Coloſſ. There is alſo a falſe letter, which the Romanes haue deuiſed vpon the ſame text. That is, that the reſt of Chriſtes ſufferings which were vnperfect in him, the Apoſtle hath
<pb facs="tcp:10210:52"/> fulfilled in his owne perſon, for the more full &amp; perfect redemption of the Churche, wherevpon they grounde the merites of Saincts, ſatiſfaction by our owne works, making Chriſtes paſſion vnſufficient of it ſelfe for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to other places of the ſcripture:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24</note> As this, By Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſtripes we are healed: &amp; thoſe:<note place="margin">Heb. 7 25.</note> Chriſt is able perfectly to ſaue them that come vnto God by him, ſéeing he euer liueth to make interceſſion for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Heb. 9.12.</note> &amp; Chriſt by his owne bloud entred in once vnto the holy place, &amp; obteined eternall redemption for vs. For if the bloud of buls, and of goates, and the aſhes of an heifer, ſprinkling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are vncleane, ſanctified as touching the purifying of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh: how much more ſhall the bloud of Chriſt, whiche through the eternall ſpirite offered him ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpotte to God, purge your conſcience from dead works to ſerue the liuing god? And agayne,<note place="margin">Heb 10.14</note> With one offering hath he conſecrated for euer them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Héere the Apoſtle teacheth vs perfect rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption by our ſauiour Chriſt only, and by no other. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, which techeth vs other ſauiours
<pb facs="tcp:10210:52"/> beſide Ieſus Chriſt, is an heretical &amp; falſe letter, not to be receiued. Likewiſe in theſe words: The father is greater tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.28.</note> there is a true and a falſe letter. The true letter is this: The father is greater than Chriſt as touching his manhood. The falſe letter is this: The father as touching Chriſtes godhead is greter than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne. The falſe letter killeth, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true letter is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Neuertheleſſe, as the true letter is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways commodious &amp; neceſſary to be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo in ſome reſpect it may truly be ſaid that it killeth rather than giueth life: as if we reſt vpon the letter of any hiſtorie or propheſie, &amp; neglect the moral &amp; myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie therin conteined, or if we take part of the letter, &amp; not the whole: or if we take the letter in ſtead of the figure and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie, where a figure or allegory is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily vnderſtanded. As for example: If we omit the morall and allegorie of the Prophet Abdias before noted, &amp; reſt only vpon the letter which perteineth nothing vnto vs, it profiteth vs little. Likewiſe in the commaundements: thou ſhalt do no murther, thou ſhalte not commit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultrie, thou ſhalt not ſteale, and ſo foorth:
<pb facs="tcp:10210:53"/> this is a true letter, that thereby we are forbidden actual murder, &amp; actual adultry, and theft. This is but a péece of the letter, and not the whole: the whole letter is that therby we are not only forbidden to ſtay a man, to defile a woman, &amp; to take away an other mans goodes ſecretly, or openly, out of his houſe, or by the highe way ſide: but alſo we are therby co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded not to hurt our neighbour neither in worde nor thought, &amp; to abſteine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all maner of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, deceitful &amp; hurtful dealings, &amp; alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al filthy cogitations inwardly, no leſſe than fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> violent, manifeſt, &amp; couetous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons outwardly.<note place="margin">Mat 5. ver. 11. &amp;. 27.</note> Thus our Sauiour him ſelfe expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements in the Goſpel. He that taketh part of this letter, and not the whole, is deceiued, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadeth him ſelfe that he walketh in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in abſteining fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> outward actions that are euill, whereas his heart is full of deadly poyſon. In this reſpect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,<note place="margin">Luk. 20.17 Act 4 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 10. ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;. 11. &amp; 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; cap. 15.1.</note> rather than profiteth. Finally where our ſauiour calleth himſelf a ſtone, a dore a vine, &amp; a ſhepherd, &amp; where we are called ſhéepe by a figuratiue ſpéeche: if we take the letter in ſtead of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſterie, the letter
<pb facs="tcp:10210:53"/> killeth. And in all the Parables of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, as in the Parable of the ſower,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.3.</note> and ſo foorth, where a figure is neceſſarily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded, if we vnderſtande the earthly and not the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſower, the letter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth not. Yet this I will ſay for the true letter of all neceſſarie allegories, that it may be likened to the wine veſſels, &amp; the allegory to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wine. He that will haue his wine ſafe &amp; ſweete, muſt take heede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his veſſels be not broken, &amp; that they be wel ſeaſoned, for if they be broken his wine wil be ſpilt, &amp; if they be not wel ſeaſoned, it wil be ſoure: So if we wil haue ſounde doctrine, we muſte be ſure that we alter not the letter, that we neither adde to it, nor take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, for if we do, we ſhall haue ſoure wine, I meane, we ſhall haue falſe doctrine. As in thoſe words: Excepte you eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and of his Saincts, and drinke their bloud, you haue no life in you. Here is an addition to the letter, which maketh much for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſtes, that teache men to call vpon Saincts that are dead, &amp; to pray vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we can not do without a fayth and a beléefe in them, as it is written: Howe
<pb facs="tcp:10210:54"/> ſhal they cal on him,<note place="margin">Ro. 10 14.</note> in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue not beléeued? But faith &amp; beléefe is proper on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto almighty God, and is the meane wherby we do eate the fleſhe, &amp; drinke the bloud of our ſauiour Chriſt. As he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs in theſe words:<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.35.</note> I am the bread of life, he that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to me, ſhal not hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and he that beleeueth in me, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thirſt.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.54.</note> The reaſon is this: whoſoeuer eateth my fleſhe, and drinketh my bloud, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day. For my fleſhe is meate in déede, &amp; my bloud is drinke in déede. Héere our ſauiour techeth vs that he is bread, he is meat &amp; drinke vnto vs, we muſt come vnto him, we muſte eate him, we muſte drink him, &amp; we ſhal not hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger nor thyrſt for euer. And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane wherby we do eat his fleſh, &amp; drink his bloud, to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; our thyrſt: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beleue in him. For he ſaith: He that beléeueth in me ſhal neuer thyrſt. Therfore if the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel might be permitted to add vnto the letter, ſaying thus: Except ye eate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh of the ſonne of man, &amp; of his Saincts, and ſo foorth: they might eaſily proue that it is lawfull for vs to put our
<pb facs="tcp:10210:54"/> truſt in ſaincts, &amp; to beléeue in them, as in ſauiours, &amp; conſequently that it is good &amp; neceſſary to pray vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our without any additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith:<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.53.</note> Except ye eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, &amp; drink his bloud, ye haue no life in you. This is the true letter, which if we kéepe in this place, &amp; in al other places of the ſcripture without any alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it ſerueth ſo for the confirmation of the truth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries can haue no aduantage agaynſt it. But if we take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter only without the true feare &amp; meaning therof, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth therby, auayleth vs nothing, for that is to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſel without wine, whiche dothe vs no good. Therefore in this reſpecte alſo it may be truely ſayde: The letter rather killeth than giueth life. Moreouer, for the better vnderſtanding of the Apoſtles wordes, it is to be noted,<note place="margin">The letter diuerſly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded.</note> that the true letter is diuerſly vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſcripture. Firſt the playn ſenſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture without any morall or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, is called y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> letter: of the which it hath bin ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſpoken before. Secondly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, morally, &amp; allegorically, as it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teineth
<pb facs="tcp:10210:55"/> all neceſſarie knowledge without the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God, whiche cauſeth vs to bring foorth fruites according to the ſame, may be called a letter that killeth. They that are deſtitute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of God (without the which no man can liue, although he haue al knowledge) are like the high way ſide, or the ſtony grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, or the briers and brambles, in the which, and among the which the good ſéede can not proſper and bring foorth fruit. This knowledge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpirite of God, is a letter that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> damnation of men, rather than profiteth them. For our Sauiour ſayth: that ſeruant that knew his maſters will,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.47</note> and prepared not him ſelfe, neither did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes. Of this damnable letter it maye ſéeme that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, where he ſayth:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.27.</note> Shal not vncircunciſion (which is by nature) if it kéepe the lawe, iudge thée, whiche by the letter and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, art a tranſgreſſour of the law? For he is not a Iewe whiche is one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, neither is that circumciſion which is outward in the fleſh: but he is a Iewe which is one within, and the circumciſion
<pb facs="tcp:10210:55"/> is of the heart in the ſpirite, not in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whoſe praiſe is not of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but of God. Thirdly, not only al knowledge without good works, but alſo external works that are done in hypocriſte, as comming to the church to heare the word of God, without a deſire to be reformed thereby: may be called a letter that killeth. When men come to beare what the Preacher can do, and not to learne what they them ſelues ought to do: when men pray with their lippes, and not with their hearts, or do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good worke for vayne glory, or to get them a name among men, &amp; ſo foorth: this is a letter that profiteth not. Of this letter the Apoſtle ſéemeth to ſpeake, where he ſayth:<note place="margin">Rom. 7.6.</note> Nowe are we deliuered from the law, béeing dead vnto it, wherin we were holden, that we ſhuld ſerue in newneſſe of ſpirite, &amp; not in the oldneſſe of the letter. Finally the law co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered by it ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, is called a letter that killeth: As where the Apoſtle ſayth:<note place="margin">2. Cor</note> God hath made vs able miniſters of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not of the letter, but of the ſpirite: for the letter killeth, but the ſpirite giueth life. Where the Apoſtle writeth theſe
<pb facs="tcp:10210:56"/> words, he diſputeth agaynſt falſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that receyued Chriſt, but not aright, for they ioyned the law with Chriſt as a neceſſary part of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they would not acknowledge Chriſt of him ſelfe to be a ſufficient ſauiour, they ioyned the lawe with Chriſt, as felow in office with him, in working our ſaluation, making him to be but halfe a ſauiour, alleaging for their purpoſe the glorious promulgation of the lawe:<note place="margin">Exo. 19.16.</note> as that it was giuen with thunder and lightening, with the ſound of a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,<note place="margin">Exo. 34.30</note> with fire and great ſmoke. Alſo when Moſes came from the mounte with the two tables, his face did ſo ſhine that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were not able to behold the brightnes therof.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.11</note> Vnto this the Apoſtle anſwereth, that the glory of the Goſpel darkneth the glory of the law. For the law was giuen but for a tyme, but the glory of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell continueth vnto the ende. Alſo as the brightneſſe of Moſes face was glorious, ſo the vayle wherwith he was couered, was a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.13</note> &amp; a type of infidelity in the people. But through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God offred by the Goſpel,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.18</note> we are made perfect, &amp; are changed into the image of his glory,
<pb facs="tcp:10210:56"/> and are able as it were in a glaſſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſame with open face. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more to deface the law, béeing compared with Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.9.</note> he calleth it the miniſtery of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, &amp; a letter that killeth. For through our default it killeth after a ſort, in that it layeth our iniquities before vs, &amp; letteth vs ſée in our ſelues the image of death through ſinne, wherby (as much as lieth in it) it caſteth vs down into the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable pit of deſperation, &amp; there leaueth vs ſore wounded, without al hope of life. But the ſpirit, that is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell (by meanes wherof the ſpirit of God worketh in vs a true fayth) quickneth vs agayn, &amp; exalteth vs into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where we ſhal liue foreuer in deſpite of all our enimies, through the benefit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good Samaritane our ſauiour Chriſt.<note place="margin">Luk. 10 53</note> Thus we may ſee how it is true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle ſayth: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter killeth, but the ſpirit giueth life. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in ſome reſpecte, and in ſome ſenſe, the letter is profitable, as I haue ſayde: and alſo the Apoſtle teacheth vs, that the ſame let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or law, which killeth, is not voyde of profite. For he ſayth:<note place="margin">Gal. 3.14.</note> The law was our Scholemaſter to bring vs to Chriſt, that
<pb facs="tcp:10210:57"/> we might be made righteous by fayth. If then it did bring vs to Chriſt, we had no ſmall profite therby. And agayn he ſayth: The law is holy,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12.</note> &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement is holy, and iuſt, and good. Was that then which is good, made death vnto men? God forbid: but ſinne, that it might appeare ſinne, wrought death in me by that which is good, that ſinne mighte be out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſinfull, by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. For we know that the law is ſpirituall, but I am carnall, tolde vnder ſinne. Héere the Apoſtle expoundeth him ſelfe, &amp; ſheweth after what ſort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter or the law killeth, &amp; yet neuertheleſſe it remayneth profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, holy, ſpiritual, good, &amp; iuſt. Thus much of the letter, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuers ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therof, and what letter it is that kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, how it killeth, &amp; how it profiteth. God graunt vs al the true vnderſtanding and knowledge of his worde, with a readie mind &amp; wil to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, that bringing foorth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruites of the ſpirite, we may liue for euer in heauen with almightie God. To whom the father, the ſonne, &amp; the holy ghoſt, thrée perſons and one God, be all prayſe, honor, &amp; glory, for euer. So be it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:10210:57"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the print.</head>
            <p>The firſt number ſignifieth the leafe of the Booke, the ſeconde the page of the leafe, and the thirde the line.</p>
            <p>The thirde leafe, the ſecond page, and the eyght line, for ſuccour, reade fauour. 15. 1. 17. for <hi>Thir.</hi> reade <hi>Tſir.</hi> 20. 1. 7. for higher thou, reade higher than thou. 23. 2. 17. for byd, reade hyd. 25. 2. 24. for godly, reade goodly. 26. 1. 13. for ſuffereth, reade ſuffered. 27. 2. 6. for deciſion, reade deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. 54. 1. 13. for feare, reade ſence.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
